精通Android触摸系统
Mastering the Android Touch System
翻译:@Ocean-藏心  推荐:★★★★☆
简介:略有枯燥,但内容清晰,很有广度深度
欢迎大家
So welcome everyone
饭吃饱了吧
welcome back from lunch
吃饱后就要跟我来搬砖了
i hope it was delicious
我是大卫-史密斯
my name is Dave Smith
今天下午我们要讨论的是
and we'll gonna talk about here this afternoon
如何精通Android的触摸系统
is mastering the android touch system
在我们开始讨论之前
so before we get started
我先自报家门一下
just a little bit about myself
我刚说了我叫大卫
i said my name is Dave
我在Double Encore工作
i work for Double Encore
公司位于丹佛市,为客户做一些定制开发
a company based on Denver,does contract Denver development
我主要关注ROM的定制开发
i primarily focus on ROM customization
以及一些嵌入式的应用在那儿
and android embedded applications there
不过干的活一般也就是些应用开发
and do basically is application development
或者做系统镜像的定制
or customization of the system images
当然这些都是根据客户的需求来定做的
for different clients we have in that regard
之前,我是个电子工程师
in the previous life,i was an Electronic Engineer
我搞过无线电链路,用于油气监控
i used to develop Radio Links for oil and gas monitoring.
在我从事移动开发之前
before i get into the mobile
我还跟人写过一本书
i am also the co-author
由Apress出版的"Android 秘诀"
of Android Recipes from Apress
要是我没记错的话
though if i remember correctly
在展厅那里有个Apress的摊位
Apress has a booth in the exhibit hall
你要是愿意的话去那儿喵喵
so take that to me which you will
就算不买也可以看看嘛
they might have copies my books there
好吧,言归正传
ok so what we gonna talk about today
言归正传..传..传....
what we gonna talk about is
对android的触摸机制做一个全面的探索
we gonna look at an overview of the android touch framework
让你掌握在应用中触摸事件如何被分发
give you an idea of how touches flow though your application
以及android如何对事件进行处理
and how android handles all of those events
在这整个触摸交互的过程中
we'll kind of look at the APIs that are available to you
我会带领大家一一了解所用到的APIs
as monitoring the interacting with this process
和一些思路,将有助于你自定义各种基于触摸的交互
and ways that you can implement custom touch interaction
以便将其集成到程序中
inside your apps
最后讲解框架本身已经做好的一些东西
as well as the pieces the framework that are available for you
可能会使你事半功倍
sort of assist you in the process
那么,我们就先从
ok.let's go ahead and start with
Android如何处理触摸消息开始讲起
how android deals with touch
每一个由设备上的触摸屏产生的事件
so every event that comes from the touch screen
且被分发到你的应用程序中去
on the device into your application
每一个事件都被包裹成MotionEvent中的一种
is wrapped up in one of these MotionEvents
MotionEvent为你提供了
the MotionEvent essentially provides you
关于这个事件的你所需要的全部信息
all the Information that you need
这些信息包括事件所产生的动作,
associate with each event as to what the event action was
以及关于本事件的一些额外的元信息
as well as any additional meta data that may be necessary
比如说触摸点的位置
such as the touch's location
事件发生时有多少根手指处于屏幕上
the number of fingers that we on the screen at that time
还有事件发生的时间
you know,the actual event time itself
总之,你感兴趣的任何事件信息都有
anything you might need to process that information
这些信息在你的程序中都获取得到
and use that inside your application
系统提供了一些常用的事件动作类型
you know,there is number of primary useful actions
光看其名字,你就能猜出其本身的含义
and by their name you can probably figure out what they are
但是我还是打算给大家一一讲解下
but just to kind give you a basic idea
这里面有 动作_按下 动作_弹起
so there is ACTION_DOWN and ACTION_UP
这两个动作是当
those are the primary actions when
第一根手指在屏幕上按下
the first pointer or finger comes in contact with the screen
然后释放手指所产生的
and then that released
动作_移动产生于
ACTION_MOVE is an event that is happening
手指在屏幕上拖拽时
as that pointer is dragging around the screen
动作_触点_按下 和 动作_触点_弹起
ACTION_POINTER_DOWN and UP
这两个动作会在第二根或更多手指
will be seen for secondary or additional
跟屏幕交互时所产生的
fingers or pointers as they coming contact with the screen
这两个动作当你在处理多点-触控时会用到
these are what you'll see and what you need to look for
we you dealing with multi-touch
最后一个是 动作_取消
and then finally ACTION_CANCEL
这个动作会在一些特殊的情形下用到
which we will come up in a couple special cases
在我们接下来的讲解中会遇到
that we'll see as we're moving forward
主要的用法在于
that has to do primarily with
当事件起初被一个视图处理,
when events are initially handled by one view
之后又交给其他视图处理时,就会用到动作_取消
and then that is transferred over to another
牢记一点
the primary thing to keep in mind
这点会被反复强调
and you'll see the theme sort of coming in and out
那就是android只定义了一种手势
is that android really defines a single gesture
此手势的全部事件组成发生在动作_按下和弹起之间
as all the events that happen between an ACTION_DOWN event
and an ACTION_UP
在你程序中,处理一个新的手势时
so the ACTION_DOWN is sort of the initialization of any new gesture
动作_按下就是这个新手势的起始
that you would be handling in your application
之后手势的状态会一直由
and basically the state that is maintained though that gesture
不同的移动事件所维护着
though all the different move events and things like that
直到动作_弹起发生
is then terminated on ACTION_UP
这有点像重新洗牌,再开一局的意味
that's sort of resets the whole game and starts over
这个过程我们会遇到几次
you'll see that theme kind of come though couple different times
那么事件到底是如何在你的应用中传递的呢
how does these things actually flow though your application
对于每一个由
so,for every event that as generated
硬件和底层框架产生的事件
by the hardware and the underlying framework
这些事件最先被发送到你的Activity中
they are first dispatched to your application is Activity
在你程序中,哪个Activity在前台的最顶部
whatever the foreground Activity is at the top level
inside your application
那个Activity就会接收触摸事件
that activity will receive the touch event
优先于你程序中的其他任何组件
before any other component inside of your application
这个过程是经由框架调用
it will do that by the framework calling
那个Activity的dispatchTouchEvent()来完成的
the dispatchTouchEvent() on that activity
我首先要强调的是,在你的应用中,
i first point this out to say is for whatever reason in your application
你需要了解知道
you need to gain knowledge of or get understanding of
不管你在程序做了何种事件处理
touch events before anything else in your application does
最先获取事件处理机会的
the very first opportunity you have at all to see a touch event
就是在Activity中的dispatchTouchEvent()
is the dispatchTouchEvent() on activity
因此,你可以重载这个方法
so you can override that method
在这个方法里检查各种移动事件
and inspect those motion events there
我不建议大家在这个方法里面做过多的事情
i wouldn't necessarily recommend doing a whole lot with them
但是大家起码要监测一些事件的流向
other than just monitoring them
因为事件要在整个框架中走完还有很长的路
case they have a long way to go still though the framework
总而言之,这是事件流经的第一站
but this is the first method that we'll ever be called
在这个方法里
and then,in that point
这些事件会开启其旅程
these events are going to traversal their way
由Activity开始往下传递给你的视图结构树,
down from the activity down though from your view hierarchy
而在视图结构树中会由上到下传递
from the top down
事件首先由窗口服务端发送到Activity里面
so they are gonna start at the activity in the window level
再由Activity发送给RootView(详情参考:Android内核剖析)
and they will be first delivered to the RootView
这个RootView存在于你的contentView里
of whatever your content ViewGroup is
之后,再由根ViewGroup将其发送给子视图们
and then that ViewGroup's job is to deliver it to its childViews
如果这些子视图中也有ViewGroup,就递归地再往下分发
and if those are ViewGroups,to their childViews
直到事件分发到视图树的最底部
all the way down the tree to way get the bottom
之后,事件会反过来由底向上传递
and then if necessary traversal those back up
这里的传递机制是
the way that this works is
事件会在你的程序中从上往下再从下往上穿梭
the events will flow through your application
直到某个View
until such point that one of the views
宣布其对这个事件感兴趣为止
declares that is interested in that event
一旦如此,那么关于某个手势的其他信息就会接踵而来
and wants to know more about the rest of the gesture
是否"感兴趣"体现在框架上就是onTouchEvent()这个方法
the way the framework does this is the onTouchEvent()
每个View和ViewGroup都有这个函数,其返回一个布尔值
every View or ViewGroup has,returns a boolean value
因此,作为一个自定义视图的实现者
and so,as a implementer of a custom view
或者自定义视图树中其他部分
or you know some other piece of the view hierarchy
你就可以在这个方法中返回true
your application can return true from this method
来宣布你的自定义视图对触摸事件感兴趣
to declare interest in that particular gesture
到那时,
and at that point
Android框架就知道了有一个视图会对触摸事件感兴趣
the framework has found a view that is interested in the touch
那么它就会中断原本的对触摸事件的响应链
and it will stop that respond chain
如果一个触摸事件
but essentially if a touch event
成功的传递到了视图的底部
manages to go all the way down the view hierarchy
以及在此过程中,没有任何视图对其产生兴趣
and not find a single view that is interested in that touch
此事件就会在视图树中一直往上返回
it will start to work back up to the hierarchy
直到这个事件返回到Activity为止
until it gets all the way back to the activity
现在你可能对这个流程没啥感觉,
that may make a little more sense when you see
不过当你看到一些视觉化的东西时就会感觉好很多了
sort of a visualization of it here a little bit in an example
核心内容在于
but the kind of core
我再强调一下,核心内容是
the core thing to come a way with that is
当你尝试去做任何的自定义事件处理时
if you are trying to do any custom touch handling
动作_按下 这个事件将会是
the ACTION_DOWN event is something
你的View或者ViewGroup中onTouchEvent()需要注意的
that your View or your ViewGroup
如果你对这个事件感兴趣抑或对其后的事件感兴趣
need to return true for if you're interested in that event
你需在onTouchEvent()中处理 动作_按下 时返回true
or any event after that effect
因为如果你不宣布你对 动作_按下 感兴趣时
case if you don't declare interest in ACTION_DOWN
此时,系统就会觉得你对其他事件亦不感兴趣
there is a good chance you may not see another touch event
at all at that point
就效率而言,系统认为他们这么做理所当然
for efficiency reasons they don't..
一旦某个特定的View宣布了
它对某个事件感兴趣以及返回true
once a particular View has declared an interest and has returned true
那么这个View就是某个手势中其他事件的直接目的地
that is the effective destination for all the other MotionEvent
for the reminder of that gesture
还是那句话,见了视觉化的东西你就能顿悟了
that might make more sense when you actually see in visualization
综上所述,整个视图树的传递流程是
but as i mentioned,the way that this hierarchy basically works
通过View和ViewGroup自顶向下传递
is that they will traversal down thought the Views and ViewGroups
根据是View还是ViewGroup调用其各自的dispatch方法
by individually calling the dispatch methods of each
ViewGroup会把事件交由它的孩子,孩子会交给孙子等等
so the ViewGroup will dispatch to the View and so on and so forth
接下来,当事件往上传递时
and then as they work back up
View和ViewGroup就会调用onTouchEvent()了
it's the onTouchEvent() that get called
简而言之,dispatch一层一层往下调用
effectively,the dispatch methods go on the way down
onTouchEvent一层一层往上返回
and onTouch on the way back up
所以
so
我们中有些人也可能做过这事儿
some of you may have done this before
这事儿是我之前犯过的一个错误
i know i've made this mistake before
在Activity中有一个onTouchEvent()的方法
that there is an onTouchEvent() on activity
既然事件经由Activity分发下去
and thinking while activity is the top value
那么在Activity中的onTouchEvent()就是
onTouchEvent() is probably the place for
我要监控触摸事件的传递流程的第一站
i want to monitor for touches if i wanna see them first
但是结果却是恰恰相反
and it turns out the opposite is true
如果你在Activity的onTouchEvent中监测触摸事件
if you monitor for touchEvents in the activity's onTouchEvent()
这个地方会是触摸事件到达的终点
that is the last place that the touch event will end up
而且大多数情况下你根本监测不到
and in many cases that they may not show up at all
因为
because
如果触摸事件被中间过程中的某个View消费了
if a touch event is consumed by some View
那么事件终点就会停到那个View处了
lower down in the tree,that's where it stops
也就是说那个View上面的onTouchEvent就不会被调用了
so anything after that on the way back up won't be called at all
这些你要谨记
just something you keep in mind
额外的说,我们可以
additionally,we do have the ability
有另外一种方式监测触摸事件或者是对事件做交互处理
to either monitor or interact with
这种方法不必我们去派生View或ViewGroup的子类
touch events without having to subclass View or ViewGroups
而是直接调用其onTouchListener()即可
by way of what's known is onTouchListener()
onTouchListener()就跟
and onTouchListener() behaves very similar
onTouchEvent()没啥两样
to the onTouchEvent() of a view
在此方法中,你照样可以返回true
and that you still have the ability to return true from that method
来消耗某些事件
to consume those events
当我们对待某些情形时,
you'll see how we can use that a little bit
使用这个方法是个不错的选择
to our advantage in certain use cases
好了,咱已经把触摸的流程走完了
ok,we just kind walk though the specifics what's really happening
之前我说过,我们于Activity开始
as i mentioned,we start with activity
因此,当Activity调用dispatchTouchEvent()时
so when the dispatchTouchEvent() is called on activity
这当然是事件传递的第一步了
which is always the first things to happen
Activity就通过其dispatch方法将事件传给RootView
the activity dispatches that event to the RootView
RootView大多数情况下就是一个ViewGroup
which improbably almost all cases is actually a ViewGroup
或者说是个布局(继承自ViewGroup)
or some sort of Layout
因此Activity的工作是
so the job of the activity
调用那个ViewGroup的dispatchTouchEvent()
is to call the dispatchTouchEvent() of that ViewGroup and then
在ViewGroup的dispatch中会调用其孩子的dispatch
the ViewGroups will call the dispatchTouchEvent() of their children
一会我们就对这个过程做详解
but we'll look at that there just in a second
之后,在Activity中的onTouchEvent()会是
and then onTouchEvent() on the activity
触摸事件传递链条的终点
will be the end of that chain
不过前提是在整个过程中没有视图
if there are no other Views though out the entire process
去对触摸事件感兴趣
that say they want that event
整体来看,View在这个过程中的逻辑要比ViewGroup简单
the View case is a little bit simpler,certainly simpler than ViewGroup
View的dispatchTouchEvent()
the dispatchTouchEvent() inside just regular of a View
只需要干两件事儿
really only has two jobs
第一件事儿是
the first thing that will happen
检查是否有
is it will check to see whether or not
TouchListener注册在这个View中
a TouchListener() has been registered on that View
如果有
and if it has
就会先对此监听器进行检查
it will check with the Listener first
看看其是否想要消费此次事件
to see if he wants to consume that event
如果触摸监听器不消费事件
if the TouchListener does not consume the event
或者传进来的事件跟要监听的事件无关
or if there isn't one attached
接下来该View的onTouchEvent()就要被调用了
then the onTouchEvent() of that View gets called
如果在onTouchEvent()中也没有返回true
and if it doesn't return true there
那么事件就会返回到视图树上的上一层
it's gonna pass it back up the hierarchy
在一般的View中,就只有这两个地方来处理事件
ok.so really only this two places on a traditional View
ViewGroup的机制就有点复杂了
ViewGroup is little bit more complex
有以下几点
for a couple of reasons
首先,它要对childView进行管理
first,it has childViews to manage
因此,在处理事件时,
so it's responsible for actually
它需要对自己的child进行遍历和迭代
going though and iterating though its childViews
来确定哪些孩子
to determine which one of those Views may
有可能对此事件感兴趣
possibly want this event
这些孩子肯定是在当前处理事件的ViewGroup中的孩子
that all actually managed inside ViewGroup
如果你去看ViewGroup的源码
if you look at the source code for ViewGroup
这个过程是在ViewGroup的dispatchTouchEvent()中
you will see it doing this inside it by dispatchTouchEvent()
实际上,ViewGroup会
effectively,what it doing is
根据触摸的位置来判断
evaluating based on the touch location
有哪些childViews可以代表此位置
which childViews actually represent that location
意思是触摸位置处于childView的边界内
which childViews have their bounds inside this touch
这样才说明触摸事件与此View相关
so that might be considered relevant to that View
如果此childView不只1个
and it there are more than one,for instance,if there're..
比方说两个有重叠部分的View
overlapping at all,or something like that
ViewGroup就会逆序遍历这些孩子View
it will iterate though those children in reverse order
逆序是指按照被加入到ViewGroup中的顺序的逆序
basically,in reverse order that they were added to the ViewGroup
这些View就有处理事件的机会
they will be given the opportunity to process that event
通过父View的dispatch,首先是第一个childView处理事件
by dispatching it to,first this childView
之后再轮到第二个childView
and then to the next childView
前提是第一个childView没有消耗掉事件
assuming the first one didn't consume the event
这些都是发生在ViewGroup中的
this is all happening inside the ViewGroup
额外的,ViewGroup还可以对
additionally,ViewGroup has the ability to
触摸事件进行中断或者窃取
intercept or steal touchEvent() from their children
通过以下的方法
so,there is also the secondary method
onInterceptTouchEvent()可以达到这个目的
called onInterceptTouchEvent()
此方法在不断的监测触摸事件
that is constant monitoring all of these events
监测哪些流入到此ViewGroup的事件
has they're flowing though the ViewGroup as well
监测的目的在于,任意指定一个时间
for the purposes that,at any given time
由于手势的特殊需求
based on what the gesture becomes
使得ViewGroup要停止将事件分发下去
the ViewGroup may want to stop delivering those events
停止将事件分发给原本将要消耗此事件的childViews
to whatever childView was originally consuming them
转而直接让自己来处理事件
and start process them by itself
这个机制主要用于
the primary use case for this
当你进行"滚动"的时候
the one you probably all familiar with is scrolling
举个例子来说
so,for instance
你有一个ScrollView,这个ScrollView里面有一些孩子视图
ScrollView may have several childViews inside of it
这些孩子视图也同样需要交互
that need to be interactive
在具体点,如果我的ScrollView里面放了Button
you know,if i have Buttons inside my ScrollView
这些Button肯定是要能被点击的
i need to be able to tap those,i'm actually
那么他们身上就会被注册点击监听器
register those click events on the childViews
一旦你的手指开始做一个滚动的动作时
but as soon as the fingers starts moving in a scrolling motion
你的ScrollView就开始工作了,由它来处理
it's the ScrollView's job to know process those touchEvents
哪些可以滚动视图内容的事件了
that can scroll the content
ScrollView优先Button响应事件的做法
就是用我刚提到的中断机制.
the way that is does that is using this intercept mechanism
实际上,ViewGroup本来就在监控各种触摸事件
effectively,the ViewGroup is watching all of those touches
尽管事件最终是要被分发到不同的孩子身上
even they're being delivered to the different children
不过一旦ViewGroup监测到了一个拖拽的手势
once that gesture turns into a drag
那就不能让孩子来响应了,于是就会触发这种中断
it's gonna trigger an intercept
把事件直接交给自己来处理
and start processing all of those directly itself
那么,作为开发者的我们
so,as a developer
你也可以好好利用这种机制
you can sort of work with the same process,by again
把那些需要从孩子中截取的事件处理
放在onInterceptTouchEvent()中
monitoring the events on intercept
一旦你从onIntercept()中返回true
and as soon as you return true from that
你就要开始在你的自定义布局中处理事件了
start processing the events yourself in your layout
whatever custom layout you're building as opposed to
而不是把事件交给子控件
passing them down to the Views
我们这里谈的百分之九十九都是
99% of what we're talking about
框架自己干的事情
is just what happens in the framework
这些都不用你去替框架实现,
it's not something that you have necessarily
创建一个新的ViewGroup并不意味着
你可以去干涉系统的内政
consistently manage yourself,cause you create a new ViewGroup
你要做的是把系统的工作搞清,顺着系统的意思干活
you just have to be mindful how this works
要是你干了不该干的事儿,你就会把东西搞砸
because there are things you can do to screw this up
比方说,你对你并不需要的事件进行了消费
if you start consuming events
for reasons that you may be don't need them
在ViewGroup中有个额外的标识
ok,now,there is this sort of additional flag
我们可以用来
that we can use on a ViewGroup
打断这个onIntercept的逻辑
to interrupt this process
通常
so in general,
整个触摸事件流程中任何事件都是
the touch flow is such that parent views are responsible for
先由ViewGroup监测,再分发到childView中
monitoring in dispatching the views to the childViews
同时,也由ViewGroup决定是否屏蔽其子视图的事件
and at the same time,determining it at any give point
如果手势更多的是针对ViewGroup的话
if that gesture is more interesting to the parent view
理所当然就由ViewGroup接管了
and take over control of it
但是,这点也是有可能发生的
there are possibly cases
那就是孩子视图需要确保
where the childView needs to ensure
父视图是否可以屏蔽触摸事件
the parentView either temporarily or permanently
或者是暂时屏蔽抑或是永久屏蔽
is not able to intercept touch
要达到此目的
now,in order to do that
系统给我提供了这个又长又拗口的方法
we have this mouthful method down here
那就是requestDisallowTouchIntercept()
called requestDisallowTouchIntercept()
看,这个方法在这儿
this is what we look on right there
他们应该如此
they should be
它们应该在网站上的幻灯片里
they should be on the slide site,yes absolutely
如果不是的话,我会随后把这些东西传上去
if not i can make sure afterwards they are posted
因此requestDisallowTouchIntercept()
so requestDisallowTouchIntercept()
是一个由父视图调用的方法
is a method that you call on that parentView
调用时只用传入一个布尔参数即可,如果传的是true
and basically just has a flag that you pass true
那么此时就剥夺了
and that effectively blocks the
ViewGroup对那个手势的中断能力
ViewGroups from being able to intercept that gesture
在刚讲的滑动的例子里面
for whatever reason in that scrolling example
如果你自定义的子视图出于某些原因,也准备处理一些
you had some custom view that also need to process
拖拽事件时
sort of a drag event
当然,子视图外面包裹的是ScrollView
but it was inside of that scrolling container
这样的话,你希望暂时的由子视图去处理拖拽
then you may temporarily want to deal with
从而需要阻止ScrollView去处理拖拽
that gesture and not allow the ScrollView to intercept,so
你会把这个标识置为真一段时间,之后再清掉此标识
you would set the flag for a period,and then clear it again
你需要注意的是,这个标识默认
the thing you realize about this flag is by default
只对当前的手势有效
it's only set for the current gesture
因此,如果我在父视图里面调用requestDisallowIntercept()
so if i call a requestDisallowIntercept() on my parent
随着我的手指在屏幕上移动
as i moving my finger around
当动作_弹起发生
when the ACTION_UP is fired
又一个新的动作_按下到来时
and new ACTION_DOWN comes in
这意味着一个新的手势的开始,
那么之前设置的标识就会被置空
it's a new gesture and that flag is auto cleared anyway
因此,当你需要这个标识的时候
so if you're needing to do this
你要针对特定的手势来设置此标识,意味着每次手势开始
你都要重新调用requestDisallowIntercept()一次
you're having to do it on a gesture by gesture basis
这个标识可不像某些全局变量一样,不要有这样的期待,
not just some global flag,you can say
你对它说,"不要屏蔽我的事件"
don't ever intercept my touches
之后它就会永远帮你屏蔽一样
and expect to be that way in entire time
关于requestDisallowIntercept,我准备了一个例子
and i have an example of this where you can
你可以从中看出它的用处在哪
kind of try to see where is useful
通常
in general
用这个方法的时候你要格外注意
this is probably something you wanna use with care
因为这好像在某种程度上
because it starts to sort of
这开启了让孩子视图
it starts tearing the tables and have the childViews
去控制父视图行为的先河
start to control what the parent does
框架本来的设计意图是,
when the design of the framework is really
不论何时,都要让父视图
whenever possible to force the parentViews to
去控制和管理其孩子视图中的事情
control and manage what's going down to the children
你要把这点牢记
ok.just keep that in mind
好了,是时候
all right.let's look at a
看点视觉性的东西了
slightly more visual example of this
这可能会让大家更容易理解
which might make this a little bit clear
我刚所说的那些
than just seeing it all on words
首先,第一个例子是
so the first example that i have
一个很简单的Activity,其根视图是个FrameLayout
just very simple activity with the framelayout inside of it
FrameLayout里面套了一个白板View
and just a plain ignorant view
它不能被点击
you know,this view is not clickable
也不能被聚焦,反正啥也做不了,仅仅
focusable anything like that just a view
有一层背景而已
has a background on it
接下来,用户要进行交互了
so when the user comes in
如果用户把手指按在了这个视图身上
if they were to touch their finger down on that view
那么此时此刻,就是整个触摸响应链的开端
this the essentially the chain of calls that
you would see happen
因此,我们会从Activity的这层开始
so we will start at the activity level
看,在这儿呢.之后
over here.and then
Activity会把事件往下传递给FrameLayout
that would be dispatched down to the FrameLayout
通过调用其dispatchTouchEvent()方法
by calling its dispatchTouchEvent()
之后,就由FrameLayout往下传,直到View这一层
and then,finally down to the View
你懂的,我们这个例子里的View
you know,this View,
天生不关心各种触摸事件
but inherently,cares nothing about touch.though
默认的,它的onTouchEvent()会返回false
by default,its onTouchEvent() is gonna return false
事件链就会由此往上返回
and so,that will get chain back up to the FrameLayout
那么这一层的onTouchEvent()被调用
which will then gets its onTouchEvent() called
FrameLayout也不关心
and again,it doesn't care
最终,事件还是回到了Activity的onTouchEvent()方法中
finally,we end up back with the activity's onTouchEvent()
因此
so..
如果手指按下,没有视图对事件感兴趣
if a finger comes down and no Views are interested in this
这将会是你能在Activity的onTouchEvent()中
this is one of those cases were you actually would see the event
看到事件的情况之一
in onTouchEvent() in the activity
这种情形可能使你纠结,因为你原本以为事件
but you might annoyingly think that might you saw
最初会在Activity中响应,但其实反而是最后
they're first when actually you saw they're last
OK
ok..
之后,我们会把手指弹起,这次,事件传递路线又有变化了
then when we decide to lift their finger though,something
变化有点不寻常哦
quiet different happens
由于
again,because the
由于在视图层级中找不到视图去消费ACTION_DOWN
none of those views in the hierarchy try to consume ACTION_DOWN
框架就觉得吧,我又可以偷偷懒了
the framework is gonna just be a little bit more efficiency
既然大家连ACTION_DOWN都不喜欢
none of you care these events
那么ACTION_UP也不用给你们了
i'm not gonna continue to deliver them to you
所以用来移动事件以及结束手势的弹起事件
so all subsequent move events and the terminating up event that gesture
都会从Activity的dispatch
will simply go from the activity dispatch
直接传递到Activity的onTouchEvent()中
directly into activity ontouch
不会再流向视图树中的任意一个视图了
won't pass though any of the other views
对,我在下一个例子中会提到
correct,and you'll see that in the next example
在这个例子中
so in this example
我只是小改了一下下
i've changed just a little bit slightly
我用到了这个很老式的"冻酸奶"按钮
to use one of these very old Froyo looking Buttons
在这个例子中
so in this case
如果类似的情况发生
if that same finger comes in
这里是手指点在按钮上
and touches a Button
按钮是可点击的,也是可聚焦的
which is by default,clickable and focusable
因此按钮的onTouchEvent()就会返回true
and it's going to return true from its onTouchEvent()
这里,我们"按下"事件走的流程就跟刚才有所不同了
then the touch flow of the initial down looks very different
事件虽然也会从Activity出发
it's still is gonna go though
之后是Activity到ViewGroup,ViewGroup往下传给View
the activity,ViewGroup and View dispatch chain
但是View收到事件后,会在onTouchEvent()中返回真
but the View is gonna return true from onTouch()
因此,FrameLayout中的onTouchEvent()
so the onTouchEvent() of the frameLayout
以及随后的Activity中的onTouchEvent()
and subsequently the one on activity
就不会被调用了
will never be called
我看到的在StackOverflow上许多问题都与此有关
so this is where i see a source of a lot questions on StackOverflow
提问的人在Activity中的onTouchEvent()中等待事件到来
where people start looking at the onTouchEvent() on activity
他们摸着脑袋说,咦,我的触摸事件怎么不跑这儿
and saying,oh my touch events aren't here
它们去哪儿了
i don't know where they're going
这里的原因就是一旦事件被其他的视图给消耗了
it turns out this because the ones that consumed by other views
他们就不会返回给上一层了
will never show up there
问题来吧
question
如果你的确设置了点击监听器还是触摸监听器
if you do set a clickListener() or touchListener()
那个手势的剩下的事件?是的
the remaining events in that gesture? yes
所有的ACTION_MOVE跟ACTION_UP
all the moves and ups
而下一个ACTION_DOWN,还是会走之前的流程
the next down starts all over again
这就是我说的事件都是绑定到手势上的
so that's that bundling of a gesture that i'm talking about
很重要的一点是,随着ACTION_DOWN的到来
所有的一切都将重新开始
it's really important to say that everything with down starts over
这就是为啥ACTION_DOWN是最重要的事件
and that's why down is the most important
嗯,嗯
right. right
那是对的.
that's correct. ok
还是这个例子
so,thin in this case
不管是你的手指在按钮上摩擦,还是你的手指抬起
when you move your finger around on the Button and then lifted
这些MOVE/UP事件都遵循同样的路径
all of those events flows the same path
所有的移动事件,从MOVE到UP
all those other events from move to up to all that
或者说你再放几根手指在上面,其产生的事件
you stick multiple other fingers down whatever the cases
都是从Activity到ViewGroup再到View
activity,ViewGroup and View
一路传递下来,最后停在Button上
that goes all the way back down to that Button and stops there
这点我并没有在幻灯片上显示
yes,i'm not showing it at here
对于FrameLayout来说,当事件传递进来后
but on the FrameLayout side,onIntercept is
在onInterceptTouchEvent()中还是能监控到事件的
receiving these are still passing though there as well
对
correct
你的问题正好剧透了我下一个例子
so,you're really good showing my next example
before i get there
接下来是我的另一个例子
cause the next one
当我把FrameLayout改成ScrollView时
is if i modified this to now has ScrollView
instead of a FrameLayout,ok
在这个例子中
so in this case
我们还是用同一种手势
we will gonna have the same gesture where
还是把手指按到Button上
that finger comes in and drops down
就Button本身来看,事件的传递一成不变
so this looks as same as the Button
触摸事件会从上往下传到Button里
the initial touch is gonna come down to the Button
Button就把事件给消费了
Button is gonna consuming it
事件中止于此
and it's gonna stop there
之后,当我们在按钮上摩擦摩擦时
but now when the finger moves the Button around
你刚也看到了,Button在ScrollView中上下滚动
as scrolling inside the container
之后,我们释放手指
and then let sit up
这里的ViewGroup当然就是指ScrollView
the ViewGroup which is the ScrollView
一旦监测到了带有滚动的手势
as soon as that gesture looks like a scroll
至于怎么监测我随后再讲
and we will talk about how does that
先说此时此刻
at that exact point
ScrollView的onInterceptTouchEvent()返回了true
the onInterceptTouch() of the ScrollView returns true
一旦它从onIntercept中返回true
and as soon as it return true from that method
这里的事件分发路线就完全改变了
this dispatch chains change completely
此时,发生的所有事件(MOVE_UP)
and now,all of this pieces
直接从ScrollView的dispatch方法中
goes straight from the dispatch method of ScrollView
传递到ScrollView的onTouchEvent()方法中
into the onTouchEvent() of ScrollView
事件就不会再跑到Button里面去了
they don't go anywhere near the Button
关于Button那部分就直接跳过去了
they just jump right over that piece
是
yes
ViewGroup能是把事件x,y坐标转换成
so the job of the ViewGroup is always translate the x,y
相对于本身的x,y坐标
to be relative to the parent
对,每一个都是,你说的对
for every single one.yes,that's correct.
当然
sure
事件还是会先送进ViewGroup的dispatch方法里
so they still go though the dispatch method of the ViewGroup
因为ViewGroup工作就是把事件分发给孩子视图
cause the ViewGroup's job is to dispatch them to the children
当Intercept返回true时,改变的仅仅是
so what changes when onIntercept() returns true
ViewGroup的dispatch
is that ViewGroup's dispatch
直接把事件发送给ViewGroup的onTouchEvent()
just simply deliver directly to onTouch() of the ViewGroup
而不是把事件分发给它的孩子们
not to the dispatch of any of the children
唯一跳过去的是这个方法
the only one that skipped is this function
这个方法仍然处于事件分发链上
this function is still part of the dispatch chain
好吧,我重申
while,so the,again
关于这方面我不想涉及太多
we don't like talk about this
dispatch的返回值
but the return value of dispatch
是基于下一层孩子中的dispatch返回值
is based on the return value of the child
dispatch是一个一环套一环的函数调用
right,this is all a nested call
dispatch调用孩子的dispatch,
孩子的dispatch调用孙子的dispatch
so you know,dispatch calls dispatch calls dispatch
dispatch的返回值就一层一层的往上返回
and return values all bubble back up
dispatch的返回值取决于其内部调用的dispatch的返回值
what dispatch returns based on what that method is calling inside
在我们这个例子中
so in the first case
ViewGroup的dispatch在这里的返回值
the return value of ViewGroup.dispatch in this case
取决于这个View的onTouchEvent()的返回值
is based on what this view's onTouchEvent() returned
dispatchTouchEvent()要干的事儿是
the real work of dispatchTouchEvent()
把触摸事件给路由出去
is to route where the touch should go
因为View的dispatch是在上一层的
ViewGroup的dispatch中调用的
cause dispatch is what's called by the higher level of a View
就像这样一层一层往下调用
like this View calls dispatch on this View,and then
此方法做作用就像是在说
that method's job is to say
好了,我得到了这个事件,我要把它送哪呢
ok,now i've got this event,where do i put it
但是事件一旦被intercept的话
and once it has been intercepted
我就要把事件发给我自己而不发给我的孩子
i hand it directly to mine method,not to a child
这就是不同之处
that's the difference
我讲的够清楚么
does it make sense
好吧,问题来吧
ok,question
不,他们不会这么做
no,they do not
在任何视图中,这些参数都是分开的
they are separate parameters on Scroll.. on any View
我说的是scrollX和scrollY
for scrollX and scrollY
取决于你是怎么处理你的滚动的
so depending on how you do your scrolling
我们这里刚好也有个这样的例子
and we actually have scrolling example in the way
我会在此例中这样做
i will be doing it
我修改了scrollX和scrollY的值
there a modify a scrollX and scrollY parameter
因此这两个值是跟View的x,y值是分开的
separate from the individual x,y of the View
你是在讲相对于内容而言么
you mean like relative to the content
对,这就是那些参数的不同之处了,对么
sure.so that's the difference in those parameters,right?
当触摸事件被容器视图接收时
when touch events are received in that container View
这时的x,y值(注:不管是事件的x,y还是View的x,y)
就是相对于FrameLayout的
the x,y value is relative to the FrameLayout itself
为了让你的内容进行偏移
and in order offset those for your content
你就要去计算好你所需的
scrollX,scrollY,之后设置到View里
you need to essentially do the math of setting the scrollX,Y
但是
but the
这部分是系统帮你做好
the part of
那就是事件如何进行分发
having those routed to individual childViews is done  for you
例如,我有一个按钮
so for instance,if i have a Button
我先讲,之后你自己看例子
you'll see it work on an example
如果我现在有一个按钮
if i have a Button
本来其位置远离屏幕,之后我滚动了屏幕,
使其显示到了屏幕的可视范围之内
that's way off the screen and i scroll it on the the screen
我并不需要给触摸事件规划路线
i don't have to (marsize) the touch events for them
使其能传递给Button
to get to the Button
这事儿框架已经帮我做好了
the framework does that for me
只要我用上了系统的滑动机制
as long as i use their scrolling mechanism
你看到我演示后你会更明白
that might make more sense when you see it
onIntercept只有在
yeah,onIntercept() is only recalled
其返回true的时候才能被再次调用
until it returns true,at the point is never called again
那很正确
that's absolutely true
好的,还回到这里
ok,move on here
这个幻灯片上还剩最后一个点没提,
so,the last thing on this slide,just real quick
这点很重要
the last piece that happens which is kind of important
其实在Button上也会收到事件,不过收到的是动作_取消
is that the Button receives an ACTION_CANCEL at this point
谨记
ok
其被给予一个取消事件的原因是
now the reason that is given a cancel
因为起初是用Button来处理手势的
is cause it was initially handling this gesture
当Button被按下时
but as soon as the Button was first touched
它除了收到了动作_按下外,由于进行了拖动,
it receives the ACTION_DOWN and maybe even the first
Button还会收到一些ACTION_MOVE
the first couple of those move events
但此时,拖拽的手势已经可以被检测到了,
于是Button上的事件就被窃取了
but then all of sudden that touch was stolen away from it
系统为了让Button知道
so in order to notify the Button
它已经不能再接收到任何事件了
that is not gonna be getting any more events in this gesture
所以系统就会给Button发送一个ACTION_CANCEL
it sent an ACTION_CANCEL instead
因此,在很多情形下,取消和弹起
so in many cases,CANCEL and UP
会被放在一起进行处理
end up being handle together
至少两者都是在
at last for the purpose of
手势终结时被发送进来的
terminating what you're doing with your gesture detection
因此,大多数情况下,对你的View来说,两者的区别不大
because they tend to mean almost the same thing to your View
嗯,问题来吧
so,the question
是的
yes
严谨点,你可以说,按下意味着重新设置手势
technically,i guess you could say down is what really resets it.
弹起和取消就像两个堂兄弟一样,
and UP and CANCEL you kind of just look at as cousins
都是用来结束你当前手势的事件
of the same event to terminate whatever you're doing in the View
嗯
yeah
饿
uh
在Activity中的onTouchEvent()能收到事件么
onTouchEvent() in the activity
问的好.原因在于,不过这得分情况来看了
good question.the reason is,and this may not always be true
我们这里用到的就是一个ScrollView和一个Button
it just using a basic scrollView and a basic Button
所以事件的传递就正如上所述
that's what ends up happening
ScrollView来用滚动的手势去
because the ScrollView is using those events to
滚动它的内容
scroll content around
不过,它的onTouchEvent()中可没有返回true
(不然的话,Button就永远不能被点击了)
but its onTouchEvent() does actually not returning true
因此事件还会走完整个流程
so the end up still flowing all the way though
ScrollView做的是监测事件,响应事件,但是并不消费事件
it just monitoring them and acting them but never consume them
你可以那样做
you could do that
你可以自己写个自定义视图
i mean you could inside of a custom View
在你自定义的onTouchEvent中返回真,
来消耗掉事件,阻碍其往上返回
consume all those events to keep them from going up
不过咱们的框架并没有返回true来阻碍事件上传
but just the way the framework get implements.that's not the case
嗯
yes
所以
so
你的意思是分3个等级对吧
you're talking about like three levels here,so
如果中层的ViewGroup中断了其孩子的触摸事件
if the mid level ViewGroup intercepts touch from its child
那么ViewGroup本身的触摸事件可以被其父中断么
can the parent still intercept from it
答案是当然可以
Absolutely
随时都可以的
yeah,at any time
这是
uh,it's
这是个一锤定音的信号
it's a one shot signal
我们可以在此深究一下
we will talk a little bit more about that,because it's
父视图可以随时对其孩子做这件事
it's something that a parent can do it any time on a child
但是一旦其做了(onInterceptTouchEvent()返回true)
就不要想着还能反悔
but once they make that decision,they can't go back on it
一会你就能顿悟
ok,and that might make more sense in a second
好的,看哥这张幻灯片吧
all right.
这里展示的是一些针对自定义事件处理的附加参考
just a couple additional pieces here about doing custom touch handling
首先,如果你想要对触摸事件一个一个的进行处理
so if you want to handle discrete motion events
在你自定义的View中
for all the touches that's going on in these Views
这里有两个方法供你选择
then you is really kind of two options for you
一方面你可以写个子类来继承View或者ViewGroup
you can either create a subclass of a View or ViewGroup
这样你就可以来重写onTouchEvent()
so that you can override the onTouchEvent()
如果你的子类是继承自ViewGroup的话,
你还可以在onInterceptTouchEvent()中处理事件
or in some cases if a ViewGroup onIntercept does well
那么另一种方法呢
or
你可以给视图设置一个额外的监听器onTouchEvent()
you can simply provide externally and onTouchListener()
在这里你也可以进行事件处理
and do some of your touch event handling in there
onTouchEvent跟onTouchListener并不是完全相同的
they are not exactly equivalent
但是大多数情况下你可以放心地
but they're equivalent enough that in the most cases that
认为这两个方法是一样的
you can probably do one on the other unchangeably
好吧
ok
当你在消费事件时
as far as i consuming events
这点我之前提到过
we sort talked about this already but
但是再讲讲也不为过
just kind of hammer at home
如果你对某些特定的事件感兴趣
if you're interested in any action events
尽管事实上你对ACTION_DOWN并不关心
even if ACTION_DOWN isn't explicitly what you care about
但是你也得对其产生兴趣
you do care about ACTION_DOWN
在对ACTION_DOWN处理时,你要返回true
you wanna return true from that event
这样你才有机会对随后的事件有接收权
so that subsequent events will be given to your View
饿
uh
当你在开发一个ViewGroup时,这点也是适用的
right.this is even true.if,say,you're developing a ViewGroup
因为如果
because if
如果你开发的ViewGroup对
if you're developing a ViewGroup that isn't truly
单一的触摸事件不感兴趣
interested in the individual touch event
可能此ViewGroup关心的是滚动或者是其他类型的监测
maybe it's doing scrolling or some other type of monitoring
你不能依赖你的某个孩子视图
you can't rely on one of your childViews
一方面来为你消费事件
to consume the event for you
另一方面还期待你的ViewGroup能接收事件
to expect you continue to get the rest of them
打个比方说,如果你在你的ViewGroup
中的onTouchEvent()监测到了事件
so like as a ViewGroup,if you see that event in onTouch()
但是此ViewGroup中没有孩子视图对此事件感兴趣
is because no other child Views (double) with it
你就要在ViewGroup中至少把ACTION_DOWN消耗掉
and you're probably gonna have to least consume ACTION_DOWN
这样以来,你才能把这整个触摸事件链就收过来
or this whole chain is gonna be over for you as well
嗯
yes
不对,那将返回false(此处应为onTouchEvent的返回值)
no,it's gonna return false
返回true只可能是ScrollView之类的或者
the only ones that will,will be things like ScrollView or
某些视图,其定义的行为中会使触摸事件身涉其中
something that has some behavior where touches involved
要是一般的视图容器的话,那返回的就是false了
but just a general container gets gonna return false
就跟平常的View一样(ViewGroup是View的子类嘛)
just like a dumb View.
ok
好的,那么..
all right.so..
关于事件传递机制我就言尽于此了.我们的下一个话题是
those pieces are there,next thing i wanna talk to you about
这里有人对ViewConfiguration类熟悉么
does anybody familiar with the ViewConfiguration class
噢,居然没有一个人知道啊
oh,nobody
好吧,我来教你吧.视图配置类
ok,cool.ViewConfiguration
会是你的朋友当你在做自定义手势时
is your friend when you doing custom touch handling
视图配置类里面有着
ViewConfiguration (holds)
很多
a large number and growing
常量.这些常量供框架使用
of constants that are used by the framework
而当你在做自定义手势时,
and you should be using in your applications
你也需要在你的程序中把这些常量拿来用
来使你的事件处理跟系统的体验一致
to create a consistent behavior with handling touch
ok
这里的大多数常量是跟触摸事件有关的,但不全是
most this have to do with touch there is couple of in there
有些也会跟画图或其他方面相关
that are for drawing and different things but
就大部分而言,这些常量是基于触摸的
for the most part,these are touch based constants
接下来我来讲几个非常重要的常量
so just a couple of the more important ones
除此之外,你要学会自己去采矿
but this is by no means all of them
首先,我要介绍的是getScaledTouchSlop()
("获取规模化触摸面积系数")
the first one that i want point out to you is getScaledTouchSlop()
我谈的这些方法都是在ViewConfiguration类中调用的
so these are all methods that you call onViewConfiguration
你可以传给视图配置类一个context来构造一个对象
ViewConfiguration has a accessary instance takes context
然后,你就能调用此对象的各种方法了
then you can call all these methods from there
获取规模化触摸面积系数
but getScaledTouchSlop()
这个方法的名字起的真好,我最喜欢了
is probably one of my favorite names for a method
实际上,touch slop是个什么样的东西呢
but effectively,touch slop is
它是一个被定义的值
a defined value
此值用于跟触摸事件作比
that you should compare touch event against
来决定触摸事件
to make a determination of when
是否能从轻触转换为拖拽
the touch event has gone from a simple tap to a drag
理解否?
ok
你可以亲自动手体验一下此值的作用
so this is one of the things where you can play around with this
剧透下,咱这儿就有一个这样的例子
there even an example in here
你可以在你的设备上亲身体会到touch slop的作用
if you wanna play ... on your device
不过
but
通常,如果你对每一个流经某个特定View
的触摸事件都做Log输出的话
in general,if you were to log every motion event
通常,如果你对每一个流经某个特定View
的触摸事件都做Log输出的话
that went though your View
当你的手指停留在屏幕上时,
just by putting your finger on the screen and
即使你尽可能的让手指不乱动
trying to hold it as still as you possibly can
你会发现
you'll notice that
不管你的手指有多么的静止
even as still as you can be
你还是会看到有相当多的ACTION_MOVE流进View中
you'll get a ton of move events coming though
因为你的手指是个很容易颤动的东西
because your finger is a very (blent) object
当用于将其转换为在屏幕上表示位置的一个像素点时
compare to trying to turn that into a single pixel location on the screen
因此,即使仅仅
so even just
一点点的振动,系统为了探知你的手指的位置
some vibration and then trying to figure out where your finger actually is
就会产生大量的ACTION_MOVE事件
the move events will jump around like crazy
就连手指最轻的抽搐也不例外
just from them..the slightest twitch in your finger
ok
因此touchSlop就要发挥作用了.系统内部会使用touchSlop
so the touchSlop is used and it used internally
来决定什么时候
this is how they determine when
ScrollView应该开始滚动或者类似的事情
ScrollView should start scrolling and things like that
系统会将手指移动的距离跟touchSlop常量相比
is they compare those distances traveled against the touchSlop constant
如果你在做滚动手势或者一些
if you doing scrolling or something
一些由数学计算来设计的手势时
were you having to do all the math yourself
就是当我们对View进行完全自定义时
like we were doing everything fully custom
你就能用touchSlop这个常量来对手势进行检查了
then touchSlop is something you're gonna wanna use that check
系统还给我们提供了用于检查Fling的常量
there are fling velocity checks
最小Fling速度常量和最大Fling速度常量
so there is actually a minimum and a maximum fling velocity
Fling是什么意思呢,Fling是
a fling is,this idea of
你的手指在屏幕上飞快的一划
your finger scrolling across the screen
当你手指离开屏幕时,屏幕的滚动还没有停止
and lifting quickly before stopping
Fling手势其实就是
is how you,you know,fling gesture is how you do
自动化的滚动
animate scrolling
当你"飞划"了一个能滚动的列表时,
手指离开屏幕以后,列表还能滚动一会
you know,you fling the scroll list and continues to animate for a while
因为这个手势
that's because the gesture
在你使手指离开屏幕之前,你并没有让你的手指停下
you didn't stop your finger before you lifted
框架就会把此手势认为是Fling
and the framework considers that as a fling
前提是系统检测到的手指速度
要大于其定义的最小"飞划"速度
and there is a minimum velocity that you need to check against
为了跟系统保持一致性
if.. to be consistent with the platform
你就要根据手势达到的速度,来让滚动滚得自然一些
you start animating scrolling when the gesture goes certain velocity
这里还有个最大飞划速度
this is also a maximum velocity
当手势的速度超过这个速度时,就不是飞划了
so that if it's above something
尽管我的手指飞划起来
although i don't think i ever has been able to that
并不能次次超过这个速度
effectively triggered myself
但是这点你也要考虑到,你应该将其设置为飞划的上届
that you should also check for the upper bound
下一次常量是scaledPagingTouchSlop
the next one is scaledPagingTouchSlop
此常量在ViewPager中有被用到
this is what they use in ViewPager
这个常量跟刚谈的touchSlop是分开的
so there is actually a separate slop constant
这个touch slop指的是横向滑动翻页的touch slop
for what they refer to is horizontal paging touch
而不是,我们常见的用于滚动的touch slop
as opposed to,you know,standard just regular scrolling touch
这也不是说所有横向的slop都用这个常量
and that doesn't mean everything horizontal uses this
比方说横向的ScrollView用的还是第一种slop来做检查
cause horizontal ScrollView uses regular slop checks
因此此处的slop仅仅用于ViewPager之类的视图中
this is really only used in paging cases like ViewPager
起初设计这两个不同的常量的主要原因是
and the primary reason that they have two different constants
当把ScrollView放到ViewPager中时
it's to allow basic things
怎样才能使两者都工作的好
like a ScrollView inside of a ViewPager to work well
在x轴跟y轴上,分别有两种不同的slop检查
there is,on the two axes,there basically a different slop check so that
这样就很容易判断出哪个轴胜出,
以便决定你是上划还是侧滑
it's easier to for one of those to win when you're going up versus side ways
就不同的手机屏幕而言,
用这些预定义的常量另外一个好处就是
ok,and on most platforms,the other nice thing about these constants
这些常量都是像dp之类的,其值是跟分辨率无关的
is these all scaled for you
所以你不用自己去找一些随机的像素点数
so you don't have to trying pick some random set of pixels
来充当你自己的slop检查了
to use as your slop check
比方说在这个屏幕上的slop检查是16像素
which is obviously 16px on
而在我手机上的slop检查肯定不会有16像素这么多吧
this screen as a lot different in 16px on my phone
因此这些常量就跟你在UI中用到的
其他与屏幕分辨率无关的常量一样(比如说dp)
these are just like any other density independent things
因此这些常量就跟你在UI中用到的
其他与屏幕分辨率无关的常量一样(比如说dp)
that you're trying to do in your UI
这些常量都会根据不同屏幕的密度来按比例缩放的
these are all scaled for you by device's densities
以使其跟你的屏幕相配
so that they match the screen you own
好了,看下一张幻灯片把
all right
这里列举了一些其他的跟自定义事件处理有关的东西
so then just a couple of other things
如果你想达到的目的是把事件往前传递
if what you trying to achieve is touch forwarding
这句话我用一个例子来解释吧
so let me give you an example
这个例子在实际中用处不大
that's probably not a good one,but
现在我有两个按钮
let's say you have two Buttons
并排摆着
side by side in a layout and
你的目的是
your objective goal was
每次用户按到左边的按钮时
every time the user touches this Button on the left
实际上,我们是想要把触摸事件传递到右边的按钮上
we want the events to actually go to the this Button on the right
我按到了这儿,但是那儿发生了点击事件
so you know,i am touching here,but i am clicking over here
肯定有比我这个更能说明问题的例子
there's probably a better use case for that
但是为了简单起见,咱就用这个来分析吧
but that's easiest one i described
达到这个目的的最佳的方法是
the best way to do this
虽然大多数的时候,人们
i mention this cause often times people
会觉得最佳的方法是当触摸事件传递到左边按钮上时
will think the easiest way is to take the touch events from one
在左边按钮的事件处理函数中(dispatch或者onTouchEvent)
去调用右边按钮的onTouchEvent()来处理事件
and just manually call onTouchEvent() on the other Button
从技术性的角度来看,这样做是可以的
technically,that works a little bit,but
但是这样做的话,整个事件响应链
的剩余部分就被你在此处给避开了
you're kind of circumventing all the rest of this respond chain stuff
View本身的dispatch方法除了
the dispatch methods of these Views do a lot more
能判断本身是否被按下之外
than just process internally whether the View is pressed
以及他们是否消费的事件之外,还干了许多其他的事情
and whether they consume the event and stuff like that
就算是一个白板View
i mean even just in a basic View
它的dispatch也会检查本身是否被设置了监听器,等等
dispatch also handles whether there is a listener there and things like that
因此如果你需要让事件隔山打牛
so if you're gonna forward events from one View to another
那么你的最佳做法就是按照系统的做法去做
which you really wanna do is do the same thing the framework does
当事件传进来的时候,调用另一个View的dispatch方法
take that motion event and call dispatch on the other View
这样你就能
and that will allow you to
有效的对事件分发链进行路由了
effectively reroute the dispatch chain
而且是以一种很适当的方法做到的
but in a more proper way
这点讲完了
ok
接下来是讲一点关于onIntercept的额外的东西
all right,then just some additional things about onIntercept
这点之前有提到过
we sort of talked these already,but
如果你要做自己的中断事件处理
you know,if you wanna do your own intercepts
你就要书写ViewGroup的子类,以至于你可以重写此方法
then your subclass ViewGroup so that you can override this method
onIntercept的机制是
and the way that onIntercept() worked is effectively
对于每个要分发给ViewGroup的事件
for every event that's dispatched to the ViewGroup
被分发下去之前都会检查onIntercept的返回值
it'll be passed into onIntercept first
只要此方法一直返回false
and as long as that method continues to return false
这些事件们才会走正常的传递链
those events will just flow though the normal chain and
由ViewGroup分发到childView里面,等等
be dispatched on the child views and all that stuff
一旦此方法
the moment that
返回true
returns true
那些触摸事件就停止向其孩子视图传递
those Events stop going down to child views
转而把关于此手势的当前事件以及后续事件
直接分发给ViewGroup自身的onTouchEvent
and are immediately delivered into the onTouchEvent() for the remainder of the gesture
这个过程是不可逆转的
ok,and that's not something you can go back on
作为一个ViewGroup而言的话,
一旦决定对孩子视图进行事件屏蔽
so as a ViewGroup,if you decide you wanna start intercepting touch events from your children
你就要对手势的后续事件全部接收
you're doing it for the rest of the gesture
你不能只处理一部分事件,然后再把事件还回去
you can't just take a couple of them and hand them back
因此做这件事儿之前,你要仔细斟酌
so you have to commit to that decision once you do it
你是不是需要对剩下的手势也进行处理
for the remainder of the gesture
好的
ok
这又是一些你要知道的东西
so just a couple things to be aware of
无论何时,..你的问题
when never possible,oh,your question
我的问题是关于触摸事件的处理的
yeah my question is about for dealing the touch event
嗯
sure
我们必须要把事件的坐标进行转换么
we have to translate the coordinate of the touch
当事件传递到下一个View时
to be able to actually pass it to be other...
我貌似只听到了不得不
i am only  (inaudible..) on the words have to
大多数情况下,你应该这么做
you can and probably should in most cases
...自己理解吧...亲
do i should go to bubble back to the View,the View its if you  (inaudible..) in parent
耶
yeah
...自己理解吧...(推荐:Android内核剖析)
(inaudible..) because the coordinates point to your location
在我那个做事件前进的例子中
so in the example that i have that does forwarding
我的确把视图的坐标给转换了
i am translating the View's coordinates
你拿着我的源码看的话,应该能看懂其所起到的作用
and you'll see how the..what the behavior effects
但是其效果可能不是你所期待的
but that may not be what you want to happen
如果你不转换其坐标的话
if you,but i can also describe to you at that time
会发生什么事情呢
what would happen if you didn't translate them
这就会导致产生一些有点不同的行为了,
这可能是你所期待的也可能不是
cause this is slightly different behavior that may or may not be desirable
因此我不确定转换坐标这件事一定是必须的
so that's why i say i'm not sure but have to,but we'll talk about that a minute
懂否?
ok
装懂总会吧- -.谈下一个话题
so uh...
当你在你的View中重写onTouchEvent方法时
when you overwriting the onTouchEvent() in a View
我给你的建议是
my recommendation to you
你这么做的原因仅仅是由于你想处理
is that if you're only doing this because you want to handle
一到两个特定的事件时
maybe one or two specific events
你可能会对触摸事件什么时候到来感到好奇
may be you're curious about when the touch comes in
抑或你仅仅想要计算一下手指移动的距离
or may be you just wanna see when it moves a certain distance
等等一些基本的东西
or some of that basic stuff
你并不是要去处理所有的事件
that you're not really trying to handle everything
这样的话,尽可能的
whenever possible
调用一下父类的onTouchEvent()
call though the super
而不是把所有事件都交给自己
rather trying to handle all of these action events yourself
然后自己想出个十全十美的办法来处理
and coming up a right way to do that
具体来说,对于一个View
specifically with a View
自身的onTouchEvent()方法
the onTouchEvent()
其中做了很多事情来维护View的状态
internally does a lot of stuff maintaining state
你看,View中那些用来标记状态的标识了
you know all of the view flags that are set for
例如有,不可按下的标识啦,不可更改可绘制对象啦
等等其他的标识
this is no pressed,the changes of the Drawable of view and all of those things
这些表示都会被设置到View的
that's done inside View
如果你不调用父类的方法的话,你就失去了这些特性
and if you don't call super,you're gonna lose that functionality
你大有可能不太高兴,像个丈二和尚,摸不着头脑
and you probably not gonna be very happy when you don't know why
因此,通常
so in general
因此我的建议是,当你处理事件时
what i kind of recommend is does you sort of have just a basic check for
如果你只针对2,3个事件感兴趣,
那你就依据你的需求对其进行处理
maybe the two or three event types you're interested in
一旦你遇到你不想处理的事件时
and if it's not one of those events
与其明确的返回一个true或者false
rather than returning true of false explicitly
不如返回一个对父类的调用
just return a call though the super
处理ACTION_MOVE的时候,你要用slop对其进行检查
ACTION_MOVE we talked about protect those was slop checks
如果你对移动事件感兴趣
you know if you're interested in moves
或者说你监测到了你的手指真的是在移动
or actually detecting when a finger is truly moving
你需要用slop来检查这些移动事件来判断是否让其有效
then you need to evaluate those move events against to slop check
一会我就会给你演示
and i will show what's look like
你要时常考虑如何处理ACTION_CANCEL这种情况
and always handle ACTION_CANCEL
大多数情况下,取消跟弹起是放在一起处理的
in most cases,handle ACTION_CANCEL and ACTION_UP exactly the same way
但是一旦由于某些原因
but if for whatever reason
造成了两个之间存在着不同时
比方说,ACTION_UP是由于用户手指弹起引起的
there is a difference between when the user lifts their finger
而ACTION_CANCEL是由于你的
View中的事件被窃取时产生的
and when those events are stolen away from your View
那么你就要把他俩分开处理了
you can handle them separately
但是大多数情况下,我是把他俩放一起处理的
but in most cases,i usually just have them almost...
看我的手,如果你就像敲键盘一样在屏幕上乱点的话
if it's (inaudible) this
那你就把取消跟弹起放一起处理好了,反正此时,
你要做的无非就是重新设置View,等等
cancel up,reset the View,all that stuff
最后一点,除非你要全权处理事件,否则不要屏蔽事件
and don't intercept events until you ready to take them all
下一张
all right
这些是针对多点触控的建议
just a couple of additional notes on multi-touch
如果你
so if you
如果你在做自定义事件处理
if you're doing custom handling
以及你要针对的是多点触摸事件
and you want to deal specifically with multi-touch events
这里写的这几点
just some additional pieces
在你处理多点移动事件时可以用得到
that are available on motion events
其实,不管是处理多点触控还是单点触控
so there is nothing really special about dealing with multi-touch over single-touch
就系统所调用的方法而言,等等,两者并无任何不同
in turn of the methods called by the framework or anything like that
每一个跟多点触摸有关事件的元数据,你都是能获取的
that additional meta data just available to you on each one of the motion events
因此这些多点移动事件同样会流经
so the motion events themselves will still come through
dispatch,onTouch,onIntercept等等
dispatch,onTouch,onIntercept all that
不同之处仅仅在于系统报告的触摸点的数量会超过1
the difference will be the pointer count that's reported will be greater than one
当我在屏幕上加入更多的手指时
so,as i bring more fingers on to the screen
MotionEvent.getPointerCount()就会根据每个事件
the getPointerCount() for each event will
读出当前有几个触摸点被设备跟踪记录
read however many of those are currently being tracked by the device
然后
and then
不过有时设备记录的手指数可能有限
that you may at some point hit a limit
拿大多数设备来说,特别是像Nexus这样的设备
you know,most of the devices,especially like the Nexus devices
这样的设备有能力处理
that we're carrying and stuff like that are able to handle
你一只手上的所有手指,可能还不止
you know,basically all the touch points on your finger and may be more
那么getPointerCount的返回值就有可能达到5或者6等等
so you can get that value up to 5 or 6 whatever
当然市场上也有些设备
but there may still be devices in the market that
不能监测到2个或3个以上的触摸点
can't really get you more than 2 or 3
要是在这样的设备上操作的话,
随着你手指数增加到不能再增加
so you may start getting to the point where as you add more fingers
你再放进来的手指所激发的触摸事件
就会有点像事件瞬移,因为事件激发数大于可监测手指数
it just reports events like the last finger you touched is now moved over here
而不是像我们刚才所说的新增一个触摸监测点
rather than adding a new one
其原因就在于你达到了设备所能监测到的触摸点的最大值
cause you hit the maximum number pointer they can actually detect
如何规避这样的限制呢,其实有种叫市场过滤器的东西
and there are market filters for that
这玩意儿我没有写在PPT上,
但是这些东西在安卓开发网站上有定义
i don't have them on the slides but there is a define on the developer site
有一种市场过滤器是针对触摸屏类型来过滤的
there are market filters for touch screen type
用其可以过滤多点触摸屏支持的触摸点数
that have to do with the number of multi-touch points
that device can support,so for whatever reason,if
比如,你有个手势,此手势需要五个手指来参与
you wanna to have a gesture that required for all five fingers
此时,你就可以给你的程序里面设置一个过滤器
then you could pass a filter
来挑选特定的触摸屏
that particular device touch screen
以便能够支持此种手势,
这样的过滤器我记得好像叫"爵士乐手过滤器"吧
supports the (what i believe is the jazz hands filter)
意思是其能够过滤出支持这么多触摸点的触摸屏
meaning that it has the ability to handle that many touch points
ok
如果你对何时
multi-touch,if you are interested in when
事件会按下以及何时事件会弹起感兴趣的话
those events actually come down and come back up
你就要用到ACTION_POINTER_DOWN和UP了
that's what that ACTION_POINTER up and down come from
由前面可以知道ACTION_DOWN跟UP
发生在第一根手指按下和弹起时
so ACTION_UP and DOWN will always be fired when the first finger hit the screen
但是当我将第2,第3,第4根手指按在屏幕上时
but as soon as i hit number 2,3,4
每根手指按下都会产生POINTER_DOWN,手指弹起是UP
each of those events will fire of with POINTER_DOWN or POINTER_UP
直到我们在屏幕上的手指只剩下一根
until we were back to one finger
当这最后一根手指也释放时,那就是ACTION_UP了
and the last one will be ACTION_UP
ok
作为关于这个知识点的一部分
and as part of this
按在屏幕上的每根手指或者说屏幕上的每个触摸点
都会有一个index跟id
each individual finger or pointer will be given an index and an id
你可以用其来对整个手势每个触点做跟踪记录
that you can use to track them though out the gesture
ok
index跟id的不同之处在于
the difference between the two
触摸点的id是固定的,但是其索引就不是的
is pointer id is stable and index is not
我还是举个例子吧
ok.in that example where
要是我有
i have
3个手指放在了屏幕上
3 fingers that i push down on my screen here
那么这3个触摸点的id依次是0,1,2
those are pointer 0 1 and 2
同样其index也是0,1,2
and also index 0 1 and 2
但是一旦我让第二根放下的手指离开
but as soon as i lift that second finger i put down
那么屏幕上剩下的触摸点的id还是0跟2
now,these pointers are still 0 and 2 for their id
但是其相对应的index就会变成0跟1
but the indexes between 0 and 1
index更多的是在讲,这儿还有多少POINTER在啊,
以及我可以迭代多少POINTER啊
so that the index is more related to how many are there and iterating though them
而id就是个稳定的值,用于对按下的触摸点进行跟踪记录
the id is the stable value for as that pointer is tracking around the screen
这样你就能据此决定当释放一根手指时,应该做什么事情
so that you can determine if they lift up a finger what i should do now
通常,你会看到系统这么干
and often times,what you will see with the framework,cause
当你从3根手指减少到2根时
if you go to 3 fingers and then down to 2
这有点像个缩放的手势或者与其类似的
and it's like a scale gesture or something along those lines
此时系统就会把你离开的那个手指的index后面的事件
it will just transfer for the events that we were on the latest pointer
转换到这个index下,后面的以此类推,等等
to whatever the next one is in that index,something along those lines
但是这种转换不是绝对的
but it could be application's specific
ok
这又是一件你要知道的事情
another thing to be aware of
这点可能跟你的应用没有什么关系,这点叫成批事件混合
which may or may not effect to application is event batching
默认地
so by default
当你在你的程序中从View中得到触摸事件时
when you get all of these motion events into your Views in your application
实际上,你并没有监测到每一个单独的事件
you're not actually getting every singe one
其实关于这一点,就仅仅是ACTION_MOVE这个事件了
and this is really only true for ACTION_MOVE
当你的手指在屏幕上划来划去时
but as the finger is moving around the screen
虽然移动事件的确分发给了你
the move events that are actually delivered to you
但是这些事件是成批处理过之后的事件
are happening in batches
实际上,系统中的移动事件比你想象中的多很多
so there are significantly more events being generated by
当然这些事件是由硬件以及内核驱动产生的
the hardware and the kernel driver and all those pieces
而当这些事件跑进
then what,actually get bubbled up into calls
dispatch跟onTouchEvent这些函数中时,
事件以及被成批处理过了
in dispatch,onTouchEvent
不过这并不是说这些触摸点信息就丢失了
but it doesn't mean those pointers are lost
那么,这点在你的程序中是如何体现的呢
so effectively the way that this looks to your application
体现在每次有事件到来时,你在你的事件回调中
is every time a motion event is fired,and you get that callback
关于事件成批处理中的最近发生的事件
the most recent of that event batch
就是你事件回调中得到的事件
is what you're looking at
当你请求获取此次触摸事件中X,Y的位置时
when you make a request of give me the x and y location of this touch
或者其他请求时
and all of those things
最终你得到的结果都是从成批事件处理中
的最后一个事件中得到的
what you're looking like is the latest event in the batch
但是,如果基于某种原因,你需要
but if for whatever reason,you need
你需要对系统生成的每一个事件都做监测的话
every single event that was generated by the hardware
可能你要用这些来构建一个路径
you know,maybe you're trying to construct the path
或者些其他的原因
or whatever the cases
反正你就是想要得到每一个单独的事件,然后拿来用
you wanna make sure that every single point is available to you you can use
那么,你就可以运用这些在MotionEvent类中
提供的与历史有关的方法
you can these historical methods on MotionEvent
这些方法有返回x,y的,还有返回事件发生时间的
and it will return to you the x,y event time,you know
每一个单独事件的所有元数据都能获取得到
all the meta data that's available for the single event
不过得到的都是成批处理事件中的
but for every single previous event in that batch
这些方法还会告诉你,此次成批处理中一共有多少事件
and it will also tell you for each motion event how many there are
这样你就可以知道你一共要检索多少事件了
so that you know how far you have to look back
谈下一个话题
ok
这里要讲的是悬停事件
just a little about hover events
这些事件不是
these are not
超级有用,以及超级常用.但是了解一下没坏处
super useful and general,but just be aware of they exist there
它们跟触摸事件没有显著不同
they're not significantly different from touch events
这些可能是在
they've been around since
冰激凌三明治(4.0)之后才加入的吧
IceCreamSandwitch i think
API等级是14,那么就是ICS之后才有的了
the slide's 14,so we will trust that
基本上,这些算是
they're basically just additional events
你能在MotionEvent里面看到的一些额外事件了
that you might see inside of motion events
对于悬停来讲有3个事件,进入悬停,停止悬停,
so the actions for hover,ENTER and EXIT
悬停移动
and MOVE
你看,这些都是带有ACTION前缀的
as what you might see is the action value
因此他们也属于移动事件的
of one of these motion event objects
由于都是MotionEvent类的对象,因此
悬停事件也会被传入到相同的函数回调中
but it's the same object (otherwise) they gets passed into the callback
悬停事件跟普通的触摸事件不同之处在于
the difference between a hover and a traditional touch event
悬停事件其实...他们是为那些点击设备而设计的
hover events are..think them as they're designed for things like a pointing device
可能是个智能笔之类的东西吧
maybe like a smart pen device or something along those lines
好吧,我能想到的最好的例子就是鼠标了
if...my best example is a mouse
如果你给你的Android平板上插个鼠标的话
if you were to plug a mouse into your android tablet
当鼠标的指针悬停到某个视图上时,
尽管你没有点击此视图
then as that pointing device hovers over the View even though you didn't click on it
但此时悬停事件已经被触发了
those were generally hover events
这里点击设备实际上是盖住了View的一部分
so the pointing devices is actually over the View
这种情况下既不能认为它是触摸也不能认为它是按下
but it's not the same as you would consider a touch or press
所以,此时被认为是
and so at that point
HOVER_ENTER或EXIT如果你没有移动鼠标的话
those ENTER and EXIT doesn't moves over
也可以被认为是HOVER_MOVE,
当你在View的边界内移动时
or MOVE as it's moving around inside those bounds
这些HOVER事件就会由系统产生,
然后被传递到回调函数中
will be generated and called back to your application
这里需要额外说明一点的是
now,the only additional piece here
这些事件的回调函数跟普通触摸事件的回调函数不一样
is they won't go through the same callback methods
这些事件不会在onTouchEvent中监测的到
so you won't get these through onTouchEvent
而是会跑到另一种回调函数中onGenericMotionEvent()
you'll get them through a separate method call onGenericMotionEvent
除此之外,Hover回调函数中给的对象与Touch的并无二致
but other than that,the object you're given is exactly the same
都是MotionEvent类对象,里面存有x,y坐标等等
it's motion event with x,y,you know,that stuff
正确
correct
再次注意,这两个回调函数是分开的,
onTouchEvent是为点按服务的
so there're two separate callbacks onTouchEvent for the taps
onGenericMotionEvent()就是对这些移动事件做服务的
and onMotionEvent for these motions
让我们再会到那个鼠标的例子
let's go back to the example of the mouse
当我把鼠标悬停在按钮上时
let's say as i hover the mouse over the Button
这些悬停事件就由onGenericMotion产生
those hover events are generated to onGenericMotion
但是我一旦用鼠标点击了按钮的话,
这时事件就会交给onTouchEvent处理了
as soon as i click the Button,that's gonna be onTouchEvent() just like a finger
在某些时候
ok,at some point
关于触摸事件的行为是具有一致性的
that way that behaviors are consisted
仅仅是当这些特殊的动作到来时
just for these additions actions there
在你用到这玩意儿的时候,我还要给你的忠告
ok,and just another thing to keep in mind if you're playing around with this stuff
默认地,在holo主题下,所有的可绘制对象
by default,none of the drawables in the holo theme
(holo主题也是系统框架的一部分)
the another piece is a part of the framework
是没有悬停状态的
have hover states
因此,当你切换
so as you toggling
当你在按钮上切换到悬停状态时
as you may be playing around and trying to toggle hover states on you Buttons
你就不要期望按钮本身的可视性会变化等等
don't expect to change visibility or anything like that
比如当你按下按钮时,你会发现按钮被点击了.
但是当你悬停时,你就不要期待类似的事情会发生
like it does when you press it
因为框架里面并没有预设任何的悬停状态的可视化对象
the framework doesn't add any visual states for the stuff
因此,这事儿系统就会交给你来干了
it does have the ability for you to do so
系统定义了一种状态state_action_hover
there is a state action_hover
你可以在你的selector文件中给这个状态设置图片
就跟你对state_pressed或者selected或者focused设置一样
that you could put it in a selector just like state_pressed,selected or focused
等等诸如此类的
something like that
但是默认地,系统主题没有给可绘制对象设置这些
but by default,those are unset to anything on the system themes
是
yes
不是
no
框架没有把那种信息曝漏出来
no,that type of information is not exposed to the framework
老实讲,就连我刚说的
and to be honest,even the capabilities of the screen
触摸屏所能支持的触摸点数
as far as,say,how many touch points that supports
在程序的运行时也是获取不到的
is not something that's available at runtime to the application
充其量,你只能做到
at best,the only capabilities you have is to
把过滤条件放到你的manifest中
put inside of your manifest
设定好你要求的是哪种触摸屏的类型
a filter defining what type of touch screen you're require
这些仅仅
and those are even at the level of (capacity resist)
基于触摸点的东西都处于manifest的级别了
they're simply based on touch point
manifest会问系统你能支持1个触点么,2个?或者5个,等等
can i only support 1,can i support,i think 1,2 and 5 or 5 more,something like that
因此如果你想得到
so if you need
如果你的程序需要设备达到某个最大的触摸点数时,
你可以把这个需求放到你的manifest中
if you need the capability based on maximum of pointers you can put that in your manifest
但是对系统任何关于悬停的能力要求,API并没有提供
but any other meta data of about the hover capability,is not in the API
起码目前没有
at least not today
ok
so
自定义事件处理很有趣
custom handling is interesting
其中涉及很多数学,可能会变得非常有趣,
这也许就是你想要的
it's a lot of math,and it can be a lot fun and maybe what you need
但是
but
系统为我们提供了更简单的方法来干这事儿
there are simpler ways to do a lot of stuff
我们当然有兴趣来研究这些方法
and we would like to look at those because that may
因为用这些方法来写应用程序时可以省时省力
that maybe a smarter approach for many applications,ok
框架里面已经为我们内建了很多触摸处理器
so there are a lot of touch handler that already built into the framework for us
有些我们已经用了不下N遍了
you know,some of these we probably use a million times over
比方说onClickListener()
right,how many of us haven't use an onClickListener()
或者OnLongClickListener()
or an OnLongClickListener()
还有一些我们提到过的触摸事件监听器
we talked a little bit about touch listener already being
你可以用于监测或者消费掉触摸事件
something you could use to monitor or consume touch events
而不用重写一个子类
without having to subclass
比方说View的ScrollListener或者onScrollChange()
ScrollListeners or the onScrollChange() of a View's
如果你仅仅关心的就是这些基本的特性的话
if you just interested in some of these more common basic features
你真的不用从从头到脚地监测
you probably don't have to go all the way down to start monitoring
onIntercept()或者onTouchEvent()中的事件
onIntercept() and onTouchEvent()
利用复杂的数学计算,去得到你想要的信息
just to get that information
那你说我该怎么办?
不怕,我们这儿有GestureDetectors()
in addition to that,we have these things called GestureDetectors()
这些手势监听器可以让我们
that allow us to monitor some
监测到像滚动或者"飞划"等这些常用的手势
additional more common things like scroll and flings
因此
so that
如果我们要做的仅仅是自定义一个滚动视图的话
if all we're doing is implementing a custom scrolling view or something along those lines
我们的确不需要自己来给触摸事件做数学计算
we again don't have to do all the math of the touches
我们大可以把这难题丢给框架来做
we can let the framework do that for us
额外的,我们还有监测缩放手势监听器
additionally,there is a scale gesture detector
这类监听器就是指用来监测缩放手势的监听器
which they refer to it as the detector for the scale gesture
缩放手势包含了捏合跟张开
but it's a pinch zoom
只不过系统不这么叫而已
they just can't call (inaudible) that
当你把两根手指放到屏幕上时
but it's effectively when you put two fingers on the screen
来监测它们是越来越近还是越来越远
and monitor whether they get closer together or farther apart
getScaledDetector就是用于此目的的
that just the detector's for that specific purpose
so
所有的这些手势监测器都是一个很大的进步
all these it is a great leaden
因为基本上,这些侦听器都是数学引擎
because basically all these (inaudible..) these detector are,are math engines
这些侦听器怎么用在你的应用中呢?
首先,你要初始化一个侦听器对象
the way that they work,cause in your application,you instantiate one
然后你要想办法把在onTouchEvent中把事件取出
and then it's your job from the onTouchEvent()
或者在你自定义视图中进行事件处理的地方把事件取出
or however you're doing in your custom view
从而将每次到来的事件都送到侦听器的里面
to feed the detector with these events as they come in
手势监听器会把你程序中所有的基础事件都拿来处理
the gesture detector is simply hand it every motion event
that you get inside of application
之后,当手势侦听器侦听到要侦听的手势时,
侦听器就会把此信息发给你
and then it tell you when one of these other events occur
此时,这就由你来决定是否处理这个特定的手势了
and at that point,it's up to you what you do with that information
简而言之就是,侦听器把触摸事件当输入
so these are simply taking the input in
然后经过计算后,告诉你
doing the computation and saying oh..
现在的手势是滚动或者飞划或者是什么什么手势
we were now scrolling or we're now fling or we're now doing this
此时,如果你想基于侦听到的手势来使
一个按钮做动画时,或者干些别的事儿时
and then if you wanna to animate a Button based on that or whatever the case may be
你就可以把要干的事情写到侦听器提供的回调函数中
inside these callback methods you could write the code to do that
但是侦听事件跟事件处理之间没有直接的联系
but there is no direct link between those
是的,你只需要重写回调方法
yeah,you need to override the method
而不是根据各种动作事件来自己做数学计算
but rather than checking all the actions and doing all the math
你只需把事件给侦听器,然后等待侦听器回调即可
you just hand it off to this and listen for the callback
侦听器就做了计算方面的事情
so they're just the computation in a piece
耶,差不多啊
yeah basically
好的
ok
但是用侦听器也有几个缺点
some the other disadvantages of this
你发现这里给出了很多方法来侦听各种常用的手势
you see there is a lot of methods here for common things
就连按下方法也有
like even just basic onDown
还有像轻点一下,滚动,以及飞划
as well as a single taps,and scrolls and flings
但是手势侦听唯独没有弹起跟取消
there is no method on GestureDetector for onUp or onCancel
这就会给你增加一些难度
and this can be a little bit difficulty
如果你需要在你的自定义视图中用到
弹起和取消事件来干一些事情时
if you need the up and cancel event to do something with whatever your custom view in
我之前提到过,如果你手动地
you know,i mention before that if you manually say
直接基于触摸事件来改变你的视图的可视状态时
changing the visual state of your view based on direct touch event interaction
你就依赖于弹起或者取消事件
and you're relying on getting up or cancel
来根据视图的状态重新设置视图上的绘制对象
使其看起来并不像被按下去的样子
to say reset the drawable state to make it look like it's not pressed any more
如果你用手势侦听器来处理的话,
你就不能得到弹起或者取消的回调
if you're using gesture detector,they're not gonna give you those callbacks
弹起和取消被用于侦听器的内部来判断手势何时结束
they're using all that information internally to know when gesture's end
但是系统并不会给你提供一个回调
来告知你取消或者弹起事件来了
but they're not going to provide that to you as a method call
我再强调一次,是你做了给侦听器传递事件的工作
so again,because we mention that it's your job to feed the detector
因此你可以在传递事件给侦听器之前,
对某些你感兴趣的事件进行处理
you may have to check some of those specific edge cases outside of it
因此你可以在传递事件给侦听器之前,
对某些你感兴趣的事件进行处理
before you feed the events in
你是说可以监测这样子的旋转么
you mean like this kind of rotation
不行,不过我有一个例子,可以告诉你如何去做
no,although i have an example of how you can do it
不要迷恋哥
hehe
你看我的例子应该能看懂基本的原理,
但是系统中是没这个手势的侦听器的
so,you'll see kind of the basic idea,there is no one built into the framework
但是这个手势可以不难,
你可以用自定义事件处理来实现它
but it's a simple enough gesture to implement with custom handling
ok,问题来吧
so ok,good questions
是的,你说的对
yeah,ok,so that's the piece
好吧,这是最后一个要谈的东西
already the last thing that i wanna talk to you about
在我们看demo之前
before we go look some of the demos
这玩意儿叫做触摸代理
is this guy call touchDelegate
屋里有没有人之前听说过触摸代理啊
does anybody in the room heard of touchDelegate before (inaudible..) used it
哎呦,还不错哦.通常一个屋子里有2人就不错了
oh,that's pretty good.usually i get two
触摸代理在框架中一直是整洁的小秘密
so,TouchDelegate is a neat little secret in the framework
因为1.0的时候就存在了
that has been around since 1.0
但是
but
这玩意儿有很多不同的用处
it's kind of had vary in degrees of use over time
是个能放到你背后口袋里的好东西
but it's a good thing to have in your back pocket
关于触摸代理,大致上只有一个函数而已
TouchDelegate basically has one single function
此函数的作用是允许让
it's job is to allow
一个父视图...这玩意儿也只能在父视图中使用
a parent view,in a (inaudible) say,this is the only way you could use it
好吧.我对着PPT念吧
but there really words designed for.(not clear)
触摸代理设计的目的是允许父视图
it's to design to allow a parent View
来定义一个特定的触摸区域
to define a specific touch zone
在此触摸区域中,所接收的所有事件
都会向前传递给某个孩子视图
and inside of that zone,forward all touch events to a child view
这个..
the
这玩意儿的设计哲学是...
the reason behind it
想象一下,一个ListView的数据项,
其中包含了一个非常小的图标
was think of the idea like a ListView item that has a very small icon
由于此图标太小以至于很难触摸的到
it's too small to actually have a touchable area
但是你希望人们能点击这个图标
but you want people to be able to tap on it
因此,怎么在这种情况下用触摸代理呢
so the concept was
在ListView的Item中的父视图
as the parent at that ListView item
可以指定一片区域当做触摸代理
could define a touch Delegate
此区域可以是一个比视图本身更大一点的矩形
that was a larger rectangle around the view itself
以及
and
把此区域中的所有触摸事件都传给那个很小的视图
forward all of those events
from that rectangle into that teeny tiny view
对于父视图和孩子视图之间,可能存在一些其他的原因
there may be other reasons even inside of a parent child relationship
要用到这样的功能或者是认为这样的功能很有意义
where it makes use of and make sense to do that
但是我刚讲的东西是其最初被加入到框架里的设计意图
but that's kind of reason it was added to the framework in the original design
在多数情况下,你可能会规避走到这一步
there,in a lot cases you can sometimes get away with doing the same thing
比方说那把视图设置的大一点好了
by just making the view itself larger
尽管视图本身的内容并没有那么大
even though the view display isn't larger
就像是ImageView视图本事可以
设置得比其内容更大一样
like an ImageView can be bigger than its actual content
但是不是所有的视图都能做到这一点
but not all views can do that
因此要解决此问题还有考虑到视图的类型
so it may depend what the view type is
还有就是你不想用这种蹩脚的解决方案
and you may not be able to use that kind of solution
为了让你对如何使用触摸代理,我这里还写了一些伪代码
just to give you kind of basic idea,there some pseudocode down here
我一会演示例子的时候,你还能看到类似的代码
you'll see it again in the example
首先,你要有个父视图跟子视图
but the basic idea is you have a parent view and a child view
以及被定义成一个矩形的触摸区域
and some touch area that's defined as a rect
你只需调用父视图的setTouchDelegate方法
and the parent view you just simply say setTouchDelegate
传入一个用矩形区域和孩子视图初始化的触摸代理对象
and you initialize one of these delegates with that area
and the reference the child view
那么在触摸代理内部,它干了什么事儿呢
and inside of it,what touchDelegate does
它会对每一个进入到父视图的事件进行检查
is for every touch event that comes in to that view
判断此事件的位置是否落在了定义的矩形区域内
it checked to see if it's in the bounds of the rect
是的话
and it does
那就把事件的坐标稍作处理,
然后将事件向下传递给孩子视图
it (inaudible) the coordinates a little bit and forwards down to the view
讲完了.问题来吧
ok,yes
(注:此处的问题听得不是很清楚,
而且根据回答的内容也不太好猜,
我就只按字面意思边猜边翻译了,
反正此问题跟本文内容关系不大)
我们这里所讨论的
so i mean,all were we really talking about here
仅仅是怎样使得处理触摸事件的过程变得更好
is how we is helping process the touch
就我们谈论的过程来看
so if it's all used in this processing
这里会把从手指下接收到的事件
might be to forward the events from the finger
用触摸代理传送到那个按钮中
to be picked up by that Button
至于此处按钮会有怎样的反应
what the reaction of that is
那就要看按钮自身的触摸事件处理过程了
as far as displaying any (inaudible) view content
因此事件截取很处理是分开的
is complete separate
终于把PPT过完了
all right
大家一起来看demo吧
let's go look the demo
好的
ok
我们得看看我能不能
we gonna see if i can be
将我的平板投到这个大屏幕上
really cool can put my device on the display
看吧,是不是很酷
hey,look at that
ok
现在大家看到的就是我的demo程序了
so this is the example application that
我有Github账号,你可以在Github找哥的代码细看
that i have my Github and we'll be looking though the sample code(inaudible)
如果你也有Github账号的话,你可以follow哥
if you have it.you can follow on our case
这样哥又多粉了
that's fine with me
好吧,看哥的demo
so the
先看第1个:移动事件日志打印.哥来带你飞
the Move Logger Example,i might go though the end
我没有必要带你把例子吃透.我只挑重点讲
cause i can't really have to show you that on screen here
这里的第一个例子
but this first example here
大体上就定义了两个触摸区域
basically just defines two touch zones
在其视图容器中
inside this view
上边的区域会Log输入其收到的所有触摸事件
the top zone will log every touch event that receives
并且不过问事件的类型
and does no checking of any kind
我可以在这个区域上
ok,this is the one where
把我的手指放下,然后尽可能的不让手指颤动
i can put my finger down,i can try and hold this as steady as i can
或者手指就自然的放在那儿
or just kind of look at what's going one
然后你会发现,LogCat中的移动事件会不停的被打印
then the log you will see just move events go like crazy
而当我的手指放在下面的这个区域时
where i on this bottom piece here
这里我按下的区域
if i touch down here
就会进行slop检查
that has protected by a slop check
你可以看出
so you can see that
此处不同于上面,当我让我的手指静止不动时
the difference being when i hold my finger still
我是不会得到任何触摸事件的
i won't be getting any events
直到我试着将手指移动一点点,此时移动事件才开始出现
until i kind start to move it a little bit,and they'll start to show up
ok
这就是我们第一个例子实现的功能
so that's what's going on here on the first example
现在我要切换一下屏幕
and if i switch
让我们回到我们Log界面,
这样你就能看到Log的打印效果的
back to the log you can sort see that in action
显示我的Log啊
pick up my log
喔,我的设备没连到电脑上.这样我就只好分开做展示了
oh,i don't have this device connected,so i have to show you that one separately
因为我不能同时连着HDMI跟USB,不过无所谓了
cause i can't be on HDMI and USB at the same time,never mind
好吧.咱们看个更有趣的例子吧
all right.let's look a more interesting one
下个例子是讲触摸监听器的,这个例子很一般
this next example which is the TouchListener is fairly basic
顶端放的是一个复选框
what i have here at the top is just basic checkbox
还有一组单选框
and in a radio group
我在此例中要做的是
what i'm gonna do in the example as i'm going to take
用一个触摸监听器取到复选框的状态值
the value of the checkbox and using a TouchListener
我要根据复选框是否被选中来决定
i'm going to determine whether or not the box is checked
我是否应该把单选框组进行锁定
whether i should lock out touches from coming into my radio group
ok
这里实现的功能仅仅是动态控制单选框组的功能
so just sort of a dynamic way of controlling the response of the radio group
比如说,
as the way it is here
此时我可以点击任何是一个单选框
i can touch on any these elements
任何一个被点击的都会被选中
and they get selected
情况就是跟你期望的一样
you know,behavior you'd expect
但是一旦我把复选框选中了
and as soon as i check that box
现在,我再去点按这些单选框时
i can now go though and press all of these
这些单选框的状态就不能被改变了
and they will not change at all
实际上,我在这儿干的事儿是
what's actually happening
我给单选框组增加了一个触摸监听器
is i've set a TouchListener
on the radio group there
然后在里面判断,复选框是否被选中,
无论何时复选框被选中
and whenever the boxes is checked
此触摸监听器就会返回true来把事件给消耗掉
it's returning true to consume those events
这样就屏蔽了单选框按钮自身的事件处理逻辑了
before the radio group has an opportunity to process them
ok
我要找的那个是..
that one is
触摸屏蔽...
touch intercept
你看,就是很一般的Activity
so just very basic activity
唉,找错地方了哦
no that's not it
终于找到了,触摸监听器
TouchListener
看这里的复选框
with that checkbox
我的单选框组在这儿
and then my selection is here
我做的是,我把每个单选框的触摸监听器
都设置到了Activity中的触摸监听器里
so what i've done is i've set the TouchListener of each those elements to be this activity here
你看,我并没有重写一个控件的子类什么的
来完成对触摸事件的监测
so i didn't have to subclass anything to work with this
触摸监听器里就一个回调函数onTouch()
and the TouchListener just has this onTouch()
onTouch会告诉我与发生事件有关的视图以及
that will tell me the view that this event associated with
当然发生的事件
and the event itself
在onTouch中我们仅仅是返回了复选框的当前状态
and all we were doing here is simply returning whether or  not the lock box is checked
因此当复选框被选中
so when that value is checked
我的触摸监听器就会对任何事件返回true
my TouchListener returns true for every event
不论是什么事件
regardless of what it is
由于单选框身上触摸监听器总是会被优先检查
and since the listener is always checked before
相较于单选框自身的onTouchEvent而言
the local onTouchEvent() of that view
因此对有任何设定过此监听器的视图来说
for every view that has this listener attached
这些视图永远都不会得到触摸事件
those views will never see those events
或者说最起码在事件处理的函数中,是看不到触摸事件的
or at least never see them in the method to which they can process them
因此这实际上是一个快速将触摸事件暂时
排出View之外的一种锁定事件的方法
so it's effectively a quick way of locking these touch events temporarily out the view
ok
好了
all right
接下来我要把两个demo放一起讲了
so i will do the next two together
第一个就是触摸代理
this first one is a TouchDelegate
这里大家看到的只是个很一般的
so what i have here is just a very basic
这里你看到的其实是个自定义的布局,在整个屏幕上
it's gonna be a custom layout but the entire screen here
就仅仅放了一个大到占满屏的自定义布局视图而已
is a large single layout that
布局里面就放了一个孩子视图,此孩子视图是个复选框
has one child view inside of it which is that checkbox
如果我点击复选框,复选框就会被选中
and if clicked the checkbox,it will check
不过除此之外,如果我点击任何一个地方
but in addition,if i click anywhere else
只要是在大的布局视图中的
on this view
同样起到了点击复选框的效果
it will also check and uncheck the checkbox
我在这儿干的事儿就是我找了个
其大小跟ViewGroup本身大小一样大的矩形
so what i have here is i've set up a rectangle for the entire size
我在这儿干的事儿就是我找了个
其大小跟ViewGroup本身大小一样大的矩形
of the ViewGroup
然后我把此矩形区域构造了复选框的触摸代理对象
and set that as the TouchDelegate for the checkbox
因此不论我点击哪里,只要点在矩形里面
so that no matter where i touch as long as in that rect
复选框仍然会接收到我的点击信息
the checkbox will get that information
ok
除了用触摸代理之外
in addition
我还有再给你看个关于事件往下传递的例子
i'll show you at the same,this touch forwarding example
此例与触摸代理那个例子采取的基本思路是一样
which is the same basic idea
差别是没有用到触摸代理这个类
for rather than using TouchDelegate
我是手动了修改了事件的坐标
i manually receiving those events changing their coordinates
然后手动的调用dispatch将事件往下传递给按钮
and passing them forward to the Button by just manually calling dispatch
ok
其达到的效果是一样的
so it's the same behavior
你懂得,你可以
you know,you can
KitKat之前是蓝色的
(inaudible) see with the...without KitKat because it was blue before
但是
but
不管我的手指点按屏幕上的哪些地方,
这个按钮都会做出被点击时的高亮显示效果
the Button highlights with each individual touch no matter where i put my finger
这里有趣之处在于我可以开始
you know the interesting thing about there and it starts to
解释转换坐标跟不转换坐标之间的不同了
explain the difference between moving the coordinates and not moving them
举个例子来说,如果我把手指按在这儿
for instance,if i put my finger here
随着我手指的滑动
as i slide my finger
这个按钮还会认为它应该被高亮起来
it's still looks like or the Button still thinks it's highlighted
因为它认为手指并没有偏移出按钮本身的长度
because as i move that it thinks the finger is you know relatively off to the side off (the) side
除非我偏移的的距离足够的远
util i go far enough away
当我点击屏幕上任何一点时,Button做出的行为
就跟我直接点击Button时的行为一样
which is the same behavior what i have if i actually click the Button
uh
如果你的目的是只对按下和弹起感兴趣
if you're trying to get more of just a touch down and touch up approach
你不想当你手指像我刚刚那样滑动时,
按钮还会被高亮显示
and you don't wanna it to still detect when you move around like that
如果你不对坐标进行偏移转换的话
if you don't (inaudible) the coordinates,
你直接就把事件从父视图中发给按钮的话
and you just leave them as they are
那么当你按下手指的时候,按钮仍然会被高亮
then the initial down will still highlight the Button
因为响应ACTION_DOWN并不需要检查事件的位置
because it..the ACTION_DOWN it doesn't check where it is
按钮只知道接收到了一个按下事件,
然后应该对此事件进行响应
it just assumes that if down was delivered to it,you should do something with it
但是一旦你的手指开始移动从而产生移动事件时
but as soon as they gets the first move event
按钮马上就不高亮了
it will immediately unhighlight
因为按钮认为你传来的移动事件的坐标离按钮本身很远
because it thinks that first move it way off in somewhere else
因此你可以根据你想要达到的效果
so depending on what you're looking for
对事件的坐标按需求进行转换
you may or may not..you may wanna do something different with the coordinates too
实际上,在触摸代理内部所做的是
what TouchDelegate actually does
不论是什么样的事件
is regardless of the event
它都会把事件的坐标设置到(被)代理视图的中心点上
it always sets the x,y to the dead center of the delegate view
因此,即使你在屏幕上用手指长时间滑动
so you can move around all day long
从你的(被)代理的视图上来看,你的移动并不起作用
(因为ACTION_MOVE的坐标总是中心点嘛)
and it looks to the view like you're not moving at all
因此触摸代理也是一种选择
so that's another option
你可以把事件的坐标设置成任何你想要的坐标,
之后怎么做就看你了
you can set them to whatever you want but that's a couple different things(inaudible)
uh
好吧,让我换一种方式描述
well,here,let me describe that this way
因为改变坐标的任务是交由父视图来实现的
because it's the parent's job to change the coordinates
所以唯一的不同之处在于父视图应该让哪个按钮知道
so the only difference is whether one Button versus the other knows
事件是处于其边界之中的
that event is inside its bounds
但是...
ok,this is
我们还是先看这个事件向前传递的例子,
再回头看触摸代理的例子吧
we'll do the forwarding one first and then go back to the Delegate
这里我们自定义一个很平常的继承自帧布局的ViewGroup
but..so this just basic ViewGroup that extends FrameLayout
这里面没有太多的东西
but doesn't really have a whole lot in it
我让onIntercept方法总是返回true
i'm returning true all the time for onIntercept
这样做的目的仅仅是为了确保
is not really much purpose for that but just so that
如果我的任何一个孩子视图
if any of my child views
还是换个说法,onIntercept的目的就是
不给任何孩子视图获取触摸事件的机会
basically,do not give any child view the opportunity to get the touch first
因为所有的事件要由我这个ViewGroup向前传递过去
i'm gonna forward them all myself,ok
因此在onTouchEvent()中
and so then in the onTouchEvent()
我先取得孩子视图的引用
we get reference to that child view
然后对每一个触摸事件
and then for each touch event
换个说法...先对手势的开始:ACTION_DOWN事件
we take the... for the initial event
我们先保存好ACTION_DOWN所发生的位置
we figure out where that is and we just save that value off
对ACTION_DOWN和之后的事件
and then for each subsequent event
调用事件中的offsetLocation()方法
there is this method called offsetLocation() on the touch event
此方法会将触摸事件的当前位置进行偏移
that we just take what current touch coordinate it is
偏移量就是传入的deltaX,deltaY参数
change it by the delta between that on initial event
这样事件每次偏移都是相对于第一次按下的位置的
so that the offset is always look the same relative to the first down
这就是我不管在哪按下手指
and that's why no matter where i go
按钮都觉得我是从其中心点开始偏移的
it's relative to where i start so the Button thinks it still in there
不过干这事儿的是父视图
but this is done by the parent view
子视图本身啥也没有变
as nothing to do with the views themselves
嗯哼
en,uh
我们来看看触摸代理是怎么做的吧
ok,and then the TouchDelegate look the way that works
这里所用到的基本思路跟刚讲的差不多,
自定义ViewGroup还是继承自帧布局
it's the same basic idea,we got this FrameLayout here this custom view
还有
and
在此例子中,我们并没有
when the view starts ..in this case..we are not like
在XML文件中添加一个视图
adding the child view though XML or anything like that
我只是新建了一个复选框对象,然后将其
作为一个孩子视图添加到了布局中
i just make this checkbox and add it as a child view
这里有意思的事情是
you know,the interest thing here is
为了确定触摸代理区域矩形的大小
in order to determine what size i want that rect to be
我需要等到ViewGroup大小被测量过后,再初始化矩形
i have to wait until the view actually has a measured size
因为当我View被初始化后是没有大小的
when i instantiate this view,it  has no size
Android会在特定的时机下去测量视图,布局视图等等
cause Android measures,and layouts views later on in the process
尽管我已经在这儿把复选框添加到ViewGroup中了
so even now,i've added the view here
但是我还不能马上去设置触摸代理
i can't do any the TouchDelegate stuff right away
因为我要等到
so instead,what i'm waiting to do
ViewGroup大小确定以后才行
一般要等到onSizeChanged被回调
and i could this in two places i typically do this onSizeChanged
或者是onMeasure被回调
but you could do it onMeasure as well
在onMeasure的回调中
but inside of the onMeasure callback
ViewGroup会收到
which is what the ViewGroup will receive
系统给它的传话,"你在屏幕上到底能够有多大"
when the framework wants to give it a size and say how big should you be on screen
此时
so,at that point
一旦super.onMeasure执行完毕
once the super implementation measures
你就能获知视图在显示屏上所占的大小了
where it's gonna be as the size of my display screen there
这样以来,我就可以获取代理区域矩形的边界参数了
then i can generate this rectangle for the bounds of my touch forwarding
左0,上0,右measuredWidth,下measuredHeight
which is really just from 0,0 to the measuredWidth and Height of this view
这些值是在测量之后用的,因此有效
now that i've measured myself
接着我就能初始化一个触摸代理对象了
and then i can instantiate that TouchDelegate to say
这样在矩形区域中的任何触摸事件就能传给按钮了
inside the bounds for what everything to that Button
最后一步,调用父视图的设置触摸代理就可以打完收工了
and then call setTouchDelegate on the parent
ok
最后一步是在父视图跟孩子视图之间设置了一层关系
so this is setting up that relationship between the parent child view
通过使用一个触摸代理来帮我做事件向前传递
using a touch delegate to do all the forwarding for me
使用触摸代理的不同之处在于
and the only difference here is that
不论我在屏幕哪个地方触摸或者拖拽
it doesn't matter where i touch or how i drag my finger
这里复选框收到的
the coordinates that the checkbox receives
每个事件的坐标都会是视图本身的中心点
will always be for every event dead center that view
中心点大体都是视图宽度/2,视图高度/2
basically just whatever the width and height that be with divided by 2
这就是触摸代理对事件坐标所做的转换
and that's how delegate changes it's location before it does it
其实,触摸代理做的跟我们刚才
手动做事件向前传递所做的并无二致
so delegate is actually doing the same things as we did here
触摸代理只不过把过程封装起来了而已
just you know special case,under the hood.ok
谈下一个话题
all right
接下来的话,我还是会把两个例子放在一起讲
so the next show i'll show you together as well
这个例子说的是一个二维的滚动视图
this is an example of a two dimensional ScrollView
此例中我创建的ViewGroup是干啥的呢
so,what i basically created here is a ViewGroup
我们可以在其中放孩子视图
so that we can stick child views inside of
但是这些孩子视图是非常非常大的
and those views are just completely huge
你看,我可以在ViewGroup中上下左右滑动
we can scroll in both directions
来把视图里面的内容看个究竟
(depend) all the way around the content,right
你看我小指一飞划,它就在做滚动动画了
you can see that i can fling this and animates
当其滑动到两边的边界时,就停止滑动等等
and i can scroll it stops the bounds in both directions and all that stuff
除此之外,你要注意到这些视图项全是按钮
but these are all Buttons
如果我点击它们,这些按钮还是可以响应的,神奇么?
and if i tap them,the Button is still clickable,right
你看,我在这儿并没有屏蔽事件,除非当我需要的时候
so i am not stealing all the events just when necessary
ok
另外我还有个类似效果的例子
then i have a second example that's very similar to that
这里的视觉行为是相同的,不过只用一张很大的图片
that's the same visual behavior using just a single large image
尽管行为差不多,但其实现机制
but in this case what we are implementing
是由手势侦听器来实现的
is we were doing all the same code with the gesture detector
因此两个例子中达到的效果都是一样的
so it's the same basic functionality that we end up with in both cases
但是你会看到自己手动写代码跟使用手势监听器
but you can see how much more less code is required to do that
两者之间,相差了多少的代码量
with you do it all yourself or you do with the gesture detector,ok
好了,咱们先看这个
go back to this one
咱们先看这个手势侦听器的版本
let's do the gesture version first
我会快速的带领大家过一遍
ok,i'm gonna quickly walk you though it
有些东西可能跟触摸关系不大,
但我还会给你解释说明一下
it's not really relevant to touch but i want you to know what you're looking at
这样当你去看我的源码时,就能看得通了
if you go back over the sample code later
这个视图中有一大堆代码是关于滚动的
there is a bunch code in this view to do the scrolling piece
这些代码
which is
可能跟触摸交互的联系不太大
only loosely coupled to the touch interaction (sob)
稍后你就能看到
we'll see what that is
先从这儿看起,首先我干的事儿是
as we're going down here,notice the first thing i do
获取slop常量
is get that slop constant
当视图被初始化后,我就能获取此值来检验拖拽了
when the view is initialized so that i can do those checks for the dragging
ok
随后的这些方法就是针对滚动那部分的了
these..the next few methods are specifically related to the scrolling piece
我在此ViewGroup中重写了这两个方法
so i'm overwriting these two methods on ViewGroup
一个是measureChild,一个是measureChildWithMargins
called measureChild and measureChildWithMargins
在大多数的ViewGroup中
in most ViewGroups
比方我们在这儿用到的帧布局之类的
like the FrameLayout that we're using here
默认情况下,这些布局是不允许其子视图大过自身的
by default,they don't allow there children to be larger than themselves
这些布局总是强制限制其子视图,
使其小于等于自身大小
and they always force constrain them to be at least the same size or smaller
为了打破这个限制,我们就重写了这两个方法
so we're overriding this method
其实这里做的事情跟ScrollView做的事情是一样的
which is the same thing that's ScrollView does
我这里只是照抄了ScrollView的实现
this actually just stole from how ScrollView's implementation is done
uh
这样做的话
we are overriding this
就能让孩子视图被测量出的大小大过其父视图
so that the child views can be allowed to be measured larger than their parent container
前提是孩子视图真的比父视图大
if they wanna to be
这里我们做的其实也不复杂,
仅仅是把测量规格改成了UNSPECIFIED
and all were really doing is changing their measureSpecs to be UNSPECIFIED
如果你对这里的
if you have other specific questions about
视图如何测量等等问题有疑问的话
how view measurement and stuff works
你可以参考一下今天早上的自定义视图课程
i might refer you to the custom view session this morning
看看那节课的PPT,看了之后如果你还有疑问,再来找我.
look at those slides so maybe we can answer some other questions offline on that
但是这里用到的仅仅是这些
but that's all these are doing
接下来看这两个方法computerScroll()和scrollTo()
then these next two methods computerScroll() and scrollTo()
这两个方法在任何View和ViewGroup中都存在
these are methods on any View or ViewGroup
你可以用这两个方法来滚动视图的内容
that you can use to scroll content around
你不用自己动手去画下一帧的滚动视图等等,
so you don't have to you know..do custom drawing or anything like that
对一个视图进行滚动,你只要调用scrollTo()方法就行
you can just scroll a view by calling this  scrollTo()
此方法
and it
此方法会自己计算出滚动的偏移量
并且画出滚动时的图像
it could generate those scroll offsets to draw the content in a different place
ok
computeScroll是用于动画方面的
now,computeScroll() is used in the animated set of things
其中用到了一个叫做滚动器的对象
using this object called a scroller
这点我不会涉及很深
i won't go on too much detail on that
但是滚动器大致上就是你小指飞划时的数学引擎而已
but the scroller is basically just the math engine to animate your flings
系统会重复调用computeScroll()这个方法
and then computeScroll() is the repeated callback that the framework gives you
来使你的动画能继续动起来
so that you can continue to animate
重申一下,这方面你要是问题来了,咱就延后再议吧
again,if you have more questions on that we can talk about that later
接下来我们的scrollTo被简单的重写了
and but our scrollTo() is being overwritten
加了个边界处理
simply so that we can clamp the edges of the content
这样我就便于知道视图何时该停下滚动
so i know when to stop allowing scrolling
这样就视图就不会自己滚着滚着滚出界了
not based on you know even if they keep
trying to go the other direction
clamp.这个方法就是刚刚用来做边界处理的
helper method for animating the fling
但是真正有趣的东西是在这儿
but the real interesting stuff is done here
为了达到我们的想要触摸交互效果
so in order to do that touch interaction
我们要滚动,我们还要飞划,我们还要等等
to detect the scroll,to detect the fling,to do all those
这些只用一个手势侦听器就可以实现
i'm just using a gesture detector,ok
我在这儿重写了手势侦听器的3个方法
the gesture detector i'm overwriting three methods
现在,注意我在onDown方法中所干的事儿
i'm paying attention to onDown()
本质上,
essentially,so that
我先飞划一下,然后如果我在飞划动画
还在运动的时候点击了屏幕
as i fling if i touch my finger during the animation
那么飞划动画就应该立马停止,
视图应取消其正在干的任何事情
it should immediately stop it should abort whatever it's been doing
系统的框架也是这么干的
which was the framework does well
我们这儿为了向系统看齐
so just getting that same behavior
我们只需在onDown中调用滚动器的abortAnimation()即可
is we just run that abortAnimation() method on that animate scroll engine
下面我们还重写了onFling和onScroll
then we have onFling() and onScroll()
这两个办法被调用的时机是
so these two methods get called
onFling()被调用的时机是当你的手指
well onFling() gets called at the moment that you lift your finger
带有一定的速度离开屏幕时
and there is some velocity behind it
此时,系统会告知作为一个应用开发者的你
and that tells you as an application developer
你应该开始进行飞划动画了
that you should start that animation
这里我们调用了fling()这个帮助方法
so we were calling that fling helper method
此方法触发了滚动器上的fling动画
which triggers the animation on the scroller
对另一个方法onScroll()这个函数会被系统常常调用
the onScroll() this one is gonna called a lot
每当你拖拽你的手指时,
so as you dragging your finger for all these mini scale delta as you dragging
系统都会调用onScroll()
you get onScroll() , onScroll() ,onScroll()
我们不需要自己计算出
we don't have to do the math of
我们何时滑动了这段距离,以及我们的滑动方向
figuring out when we moves this distance or which direction we move
系统帮我们做了
it does all that for us
我们只要把distanceX,distanceY传递给
we just have to pass those into
scrollBy()方法即可,这个方法也是View自带的
the scrollBy() method which again is a method of a view
我不用重写这个方法来针对特殊情况.我只是调用
这个方法来告诉视图去滚动它的内容
i don't have to write it in (special),just tell the view to scroll its contents
基于我们滚动了多远
based on how far we moved
你不要需要做任何数学计算等等,
你只要把距离参数穿进去就可以了
you don't have to do any math sort thing like that,just take that distance hand to the view
ok
滚动是飞划动画的一部分
scroll is animated piece for flings
这是View自带的
this is all written on view
那会调用scrollTo方法...
it's gonna call the scrollTo() that we have appeared.yes
ok
最后,为了让我们的侦听器开始工作
and then,in order to trigger this thing
我们一方面要在onIntercept中做些事情
we have implementations in onIntercept()
另一方面还要在onTouchEvent中做些事情.
我们先看onTouchEvent吧
and onTouchEvent() so i'll start with onTouchEvent()
onTouchEvent()是比较简单的
onTouchEvent() is pretty simple
对于我得到的每个事件,我都把它传递给侦听器
for each event i get,i forward it to the detector
完事儿
end story
侦听器就开始帮我做所有的数学工作了
it does all the other math for me to do that work
onIntercept的话,我就得多干点事情了.
因为我不想屏蔽所有事件
onIntercept() i have to do a little work cause i don't want it do for every touch event
我只想要在我拖拽的时候进行事件屏蔽
i only wanna do it once we've started dragging
每当我开始拖拽时,我就把所有的事件传给我的侦听器
once we start dragging.i wanna all the events to go through my detector
但是同时我还要能够对按钮的点击做出事件响应等等
but i still want it be able to click the Buttons and stuff like that
因此,我检查了ACTION_DOWN和ACTION_MOVE
so i'm checking against basically ACTION_DOWN and ACTION_MOVE
检查这两个事件是为了搞清楚手指在屏幕上所处的位置
to say that when the finger goes down i need figured out where i was
对于每一个移动事件来说
and then for every move event
我需要检查
i need to check the delta
起始触摸点跟当前所处点之间的增量
between my initial touch point and where i am now
然后用此增量跟slop相比
against that slop value
其实这就是我前面说slop检查
that's all that really is to a slop check
看似不太起眼
but it makes a huge difference
但是能极大地提升用户体验
in the user's experience of what you're trying to do with your touch
这里告一段落
all right.so
看哥的另一个例子
flip that over to
哥的二维ScrollView
the two dimensional ScrollView
我在听
yeah
两者(onTouchEven跟onIntercept)的目的不同,不是么
well,they sort of different purposes right?
onTouchEvent告诉系统的是
the onTouchEvent is reporting to the framework that
关于此手势中,我这个View想要处理的事件,
以及随后的事件是什么
this event and subsequent events in the gesture
关于此手势中,我这个View想要处理的事件,
以及随后的事件是什么
you as a view want to handle
onIntercept告诉系统的是,我作为一个ViewGroup
onIntercept() is saying that as a ViewGroup
我想要把本来由其他视图处理的手势截取过来
you want to take this current gesture being handled by someone else
然后交由自己来处理
and start handling it yourself
因此他们两个有着不同的用途
so that they have slightly different use cases
还有一点是,只有在ViewGroup中才能用onIntercept
and onIntercept is only available on a ViewGroup
View自身里面是没有这个函数的
just simple views don't have that abilities
只有ViewGroup才可以屏蔽其子视图的事件
just the ViewGroups can intercept touches from any of their children
通过在此方法中返回true
using by returning true from that particular method
onIntercept更多的是重定向整个手势的目的地
onIntercept() is more of redirection of the (existing) gesture
而onTouchEvent就更多的是
where is onTouch() is more about
消费掉手势中你感兴趣的一部分事件
consuming the events is part of the gesture you currently working with
all right
到这儿为止我写的代码
so all the code up to this point is exactly the same
跟我刚才的例子中的代码都是一样的
in the previous one as we have here
uh
唯一的不同在于
the only difference here
我们必须靠自己来计算好各种手势了
is now we have to manage a lot of this ourselves
因此这里我们用到了速度跟踪器类
so we have classes like a VelocityTracker
此类也是框架的一部分
these all part of the framework,but
速度跟踪器用处在于
VelocityTrackers are used
可以帮助我们
so that
根据每个独立的事件,计算出
we can do the math of determining for each individual touch event
手指滑动的速度是否能达到一个飞划的级别
whether or not that velocity is worth detecting as a fling
uh
因此对于处于onIntercept中的每个单独事件
so for each individual event inside of onIntercept()
还有后面的onTouchEvent方法中的每个触摸事件
and then further down inside of onTouch()
我们不断地跟踪记录这些事件
we are constantly tracking these values
通过调用速度跟踪器的addMovement方法
by calling addMovement on the velocityTracker
因此速度跟踪器也是系统数学引擎的一种
so velocityTracker is just another one of those math engines
它会根据传进的事件
so that for each event
在任何时候返回手指的滑动速度
that can tell me at any given time what is the velocity of the finger
然后,对于ACTION_UP的处理就是
and then for in cases like,when we get to ACTION_UP
判断当前手指的速度
if we need to determine what the current velocity is
是否能达到我们称之为飞划的速度
and figure out if we wish call that a fling
现在,我们用拿检测到的速度跟最小,最大飞划速度做比较
so now,we were doing a fling check against those mini,max velocity values
通过速度跟踪器我们可以轻松获取检测到的速度值
but velocityTracker gives us that information
注意,这里你看到的弹起跟取消事件处理是分开的
notice this is the case where up and cancel are different
因为我不想
cause i don't wanna also start a fling
当事件被取消时,还去触发一个飞划
if the action event was canceled
飞划只能在手指真的离开屏幕时发生
only if it truly was lifted the finger,ok
对拖拽的处理也是类同的
and the same thing for dragging
首先,我们要对拖拽进行slop检查
we have to do the those same slop checks on dragging but then
一旦拖拽发生
once the dragging occurs
我们就要自己算出拖拽的偏移量
we have to do the calculation of the deltas myself
然后把这些偏移量送到scrollBy方法中
and then place those inside the references of scrollBy
因此,过程都是一样的
ok,so it's the same basic (?) fact
自己来做计算跟使用侦听器来做的不同之处在于
but the difference between using a detector and doing it ourselves
自己做的话,我们要跟踪所有需要的状态值
is we have to track all these state values
然后根据这些值计算出各种手势动作
and then we have to do all the mathematic ourselves to pass into these
然后调用scrollBy,scrollTo或者fling,
让系统进行视图动画和更新
scroll and fling operations to actually begin the drawing and change
那会是个弹起
it'll be an up,yeah
系统能够辨别其中的不同
it would know the differences between that and just leaving the screen otherwise
ok
我会很快的把这最后一个例子给过了,因为我们时间有限
we go quickly through this last one,cause we're basically out of time
ok
最后一个要给你看的例子是
so the last one i'm gonna show you
是这个多点触摸的例子
is this multi-touch example
ok
最后一个例子中用到了一个ImageView
this last one that i've got is an ImageView
如果我将两个手指放下
and if i put two fingers down
我可以旋转这个图片
i can rotate it
如果我将三根手指放下,我可以缩放这个图片
if i put three fingers down,i can zoom it
例子的意图很明了
ok,it's a fairly simple example
这些功能是在一个自定义视图中实现的
ok,so that implementation is done inside of a custom view
这个自定义的视图是个ImageView的子类
that just a subclass of an ImageView
此例中我依靠的是
so in this case,what i'm relying on is
ImageView能帮我做到对图片进行缩放
the fact ImageView can do all the image scaling for me
ImageView有一个缩放模式,叫做ScaleType.MATRIX
ImageView has a scaling mode called matrix
所以我可以将任何旋转啊,缩放啊
and i can apply any rotations,zoom scale
等等对于一张图片所要做的操作应用到矩阵里
whatever i'd like to an image
ImageView做的仅仅是把这些动作的数学计算交给矩阵,
然后告诉矩阵去计算
ImageView just by applying that math to a matrix and then telling it use this
之后ImageView就会据此将图片进行缩放
and it will scale the Image for me
那么,我所用到的就是这些,
并且使其跟触摸事件进行了结合
so i'm using that behavior and then adding in the touch pieces
当我们构造视图的时候
so again,when we construct the view
同样的,我初始化了一个手势缩放侦听器
i'm gonna have one of those scale gesture detectors for the pitch zoom stuff
由于没有旋转侦听器,因此关于旋转的监测我就自己做了
and i'm gonna do the other one's myself
我还创建了一个Matrix,用于进行计算
then i..i'm gonna create this matrix that i apply all the mathematic to
这里我们用到了onSizeChanged()
so here we using onSizeChanged
onSizeChange被调用的时机是
onSizeChange() is called
当视图被布局好,测量好时
once the view has been laid out and measured and we know what size it gonna be
这有点像紧跟在onMeasure后调用的
so it's kind of like one step after onMeasure()
在这个时机,我就能确定
but at this point,i can determine
矩阵的中心点了
where to place my image so that was centered
默认情况下,矩阵缩放的变换中心点是在左上角的
by default,matrix scaling puts in the top,left
而我想让其从图片的中心点开始
and i wanna started with the center
因此我们做了一点计算算出了矩阵的变换中心位置
so we do a little bit math to figure out where center is
然后初次对矩阵进行了变换
and translate our matrix the first time
我们同时也把视图的中心点保存到了PivotXX变量中,
因为这将用于旋转过程中
we also set pivot that point which we will use in the rotation
然后,我们来看这个缩放手势侦听器的回调
then the scale gesture detector has a callback
跟其他侦听器差不多
just like the other one does
这玩意儿刚被android studio折叠了
which is currently folded
展开它
there we go
来看onScale这个方法
in a method called onScale()
使用这个侦听器的好处在于
so onScale(),the nice thing about the detector
它会告诉我
is that does the math of telling me
我手指间的距离...
this distance between
会告诉我,我的两根手指是越来越远还是越来越近
are my fingers moving farther apart or coming closer together
这是通过缩放因子来告诉我的
it does that with scale factor
当我这样缩放的时候,缩放因子就会大于1,可能是1.1或1.2
scale factor is essentially just a little bit more than one like
1.1,1.2 as you move this way,
而当我这样缩放的时候,其值就会小于1
and a little bit less than one as you move this way
如果你缩放的速度越快
and if you move faster,it'll be
缩放因子就会更大或者更小
a you know, larger number (on) one side of the other
因此,我们可以把缩放因子拿过来
so we can sort take that scale factor
然后直接传给我的矩阵
and again,i can just pass it straight in my matrix here
这样每当缩放的手势被监测到
to do the image scaling piece
矩阵就会对图片进行扩大或者缩小操作了
whenever the scale gesture has been detected
这就是捏合跟扩大的实现机制了
ok.so that's how the pitch zoom is working
要写的代码也没几行
just those few lines of code
我们一会再看旋转的逻辑,
we will come back to the rotation in a second
现在我们先看onTouchEvent()方法
in the onTouchEvent()
我对屏幕上的触摸点数进行了检查
i'm evaluating how many pointers i have on the screen
当我检测到屏幕上有3个手指时
so if i have three fingers
我就要把事件传递给缩放手势侦听器了
that's when i do i pass them to the scale detector
这样我们就能实现缩放的功能了
and we get the zooming effect
当屏幕上只有两个手指时
if i have two on the screen
我就要调用我自己做的数学处理了
i'm gonna do my manual rotation calculation
除此之外的话
and if it's anything other than that
我不做任何事情
i'm just gonna ignore this event
这就是我返回父类方法而不返回false的原因了
ok,this is why i return super not false
因为我想确保在其他情况下,系统正常运作
i wanna make sure that everything else works just normal
ok
这儿的旋转事件处理函数就是一大堆数学的东西了
the rotationEvent is really a bunch of math
我们要基于
we figure out based on the
触摸点0跟触摸点1中的触摸事件
the touch events of pointer0 and 1 which are my two fingers
我们随时都要用到这些事件中的x,y坐标
you know basically where the x and y locations that at any given time
然后用正切三角函数
do a little bit tangent math
算一下旋转的角度
to figure out what that angle is
一旦我们知道了这些角度时
and then once we know the angle and degrees
我就能将其作为矩阵的旋转参数发布出去
i can post that as a rotate to my matrix
好了,完事儿了
ok,done
任何时候,我们对矩阵进行更新时
at any time,we update this matrix
我们就要在ImageView重新设置上此矩阵
we just set it back to the ImageView
这样ImageView就知道如何去更新自己的视图内容了
and that tells the ImageView to update redrawn
put it in new place.ok
没有人提问么
all right
这些就是我今天要讲的了
so that's all i get for you folks
感谢你跟我一起度过这个下午
thank you for spending your afternoon with me
如果你还有其他问题的话,我可以留下答疑
i'm happy to hang around if there are any other questions
现在,我先说一句,谢谢大家了
but i'll just say thank you now
你也可以在Twitter和Google+上跟我互动
feel free to contact me on Twitter,Google+
谢谢大家
thank you very much
请把掌声听完
微博求粉:Ocean-藏心
翻译不足之处,请留言指正
作者本人有Github链接,还有个人博客,不过需要翻墙
最后的demo很经典,翻译不好的地方,请对着源码看
相信你一定能迎刃而解
最后,如果你觉得好,分享给更多的人